[本片包含成人内容 粗话 暴力画面]
[观众酌情观看]
【hollyhoon校对整理】
奥布赖恩：他们分担往事的沉重
TIM O'BRIEN: They shared
the weight of memory.
他们挑起别人背不动的东西
They took up what others
could no longer bear.
他们经常相互搀扶 伤员或病患
Often, they carried each
other, the wounded or weak.
他们携带传染病
They carried infections.
他们携带象棋 篮球
They carried chess sets, basketballs,
越英词典
Vietnamese-English dictionaries,
军衔徽章 铜星和紫心勋章
insignia of rank, Bronze
Stars, and Purple Hearts,
“行为守则”塑料卡
plastic cards imprinted
with the Code of Conduct.
（雷声）
(thunder rumbles)
他们承受疾病 其中有疟疾和痢疾
They carried diseases, among
them malaria and dysentery.
他们承受虱子、皮癣、水蛭和稻藻
They carried lice and ringworm
and leeches and paddy algae
以及各种溃烂和霉菌
and various rots and molds.
（雨声）
(rain pouring)
他们承受着土地本身
They carried the land itself...
越南
Vietnam.
（“我的国家属于你”音乐）
("My Country 'Tis of Thee" playing)
谢谢
(mouths): Thank you.
（闲聊声）
(indistinct chatter)
（鼓掌）
(applause)
我要告诉大家 回顾这些岁月
I can tell you, as I look back
over those months and years,
我们已经见过你们这些
that we have met with the
wives and the mothers
战俘的母亲和妻子
of those of you who were prisoners of war,
她们过去和现在都是我此生所见
they were and are the bravest,
most magnificent women
最勇敢和最伟大的女性
I have ever met in my life.
现在 如果给我递上酒杯
And now, if they will give me
my official toasting glass,
我提议敬酒
I will propose the toast.
今晚..
Tonight...
1973年5月24日
NARRATOR: On May 24, 1973,
尼克松总统邀请
President Nixon invited
所有遣返战俘和他们的家属
all the returned prisoners
of war and their families
到华盛顿
to Washington.
其中包括埃弗雷特.阿尔瓦雷茨
Among them was Everett Alvarez,
在北越第一个被击落的飞行员
the first pilot shot
down over North Vietnam.
阿尔瓦雷茨：有时我感到
EVERETT ALVAREZ: Sometimes,
I feel too much attention
对我们战俘的关注太多了
was being paid to us, the P.O.W.s.
那些打过仗的可怜人 那些孩子呢？
And what about the poor guys
that fought the war, those kids?
他们回家 失去手脚..
You know, that came home,
um, you know, amputees...
因战争而负伤
Uh, wounded with the injuries of war.
他们怎么办？
What about them?
我们有自己的挑战
We had our own challenges,
关键是面对
and the key was to, to face these
和维护我们的荣誉
and yet maintain our, our honor.
就是这样
That's what it was.
哈尔.库什纳医生
NARRATOR: Dr. Hal Kushner,
被囚禁5年多
who had been a prisoner
for more than five years,
无法出席
was unable to attend.
他在福奇谷与家人团聚
He was reunited with his
family at Valley Forge.
库什纳：我们飞往宾州的福奇谷
HAL KUSHNER: We flew to
Valley Forge, Pennsylvania.
我从直升机下来 看到我妻子..
And I came off the helicopter
and I saw my wife...
和我女儿
...and my daughter,
她2岁半以后就没见过我
who I hadn't seen since she was 2 1/2
她生于1963年
And she was born in 1963.
她10岁了
So she was ten years old.
我从未谋面的儿子
And my son, who I had never seen,
差1个星期就是他5岁生日
a week before his fifth birthday.
他穿着小外套 打着小领带
And he had on a little
tie and a little coat.
还有我的爸爸妈妈
And my mom and dad.
我母亲激动得不能自已
And my mother was just
overcome with emotion.
我只是..
And I just...
那是个不可思议的时刻
It was just an incomprehensible moment.
我们每个人互相拥抱
And we hugged everybody.
我的小儿子有一面美国国旗
And my little boy had a
flag, American flag.
象许多战俘的婚姻一样
NARRATOR: Like many P.O.W. marriages,
哈尔.库什纳也将无法幸免
Hal Kushner's would not survive.
《越南战争》
[翻译：水山]
【hollyhoon校对整理】
1973年3月29日
On March 29, 1973,
最后一支美军离开南越
the last American troops
left South Vietnam.
剩下不到200名海军陆战队员
Fewer than 200 Marines would remain,
派驻保卫领事处
assigned to guard consular offices
和美国大使馆
and the American Embassy
和其他在西贡的机构
and other installations in Saigon.
数千其他美国人 包括中情局特工
Thousands of other Americans,
including C.I.A. agents,
外交官和承包商
diplomats, and contractors,
也留在越南
stayed behind, as well.
接下来两年里
Over the next two years,
南北越双方的武装
the forces of North and South Vietnam
将继续互相残杀
would continue to savage one another.
越南人民会发现自己
And the Vietnamese people
would find themselves
又回到了起点
back where they were at the beginning,
被一场看来永无休止的内战所吞噬
engulfed in an apparently endless civil war
为无法预知的未来而彷徨
and struggling over what kind
of future they would have.
对于美国 作战确实结束了
For the United States, combat did end,
但关于战争的争论还没有
but controversy over the war did not.
奥布赖恩：对越南最合适的说法
TIM O'BRIEN: The best you
could say about Vietnam
就是为了不确定的原因
was that certain blood was being shed
确实流了血
for uncertain reasons.
流血是肯定的
The blood was for sure...
死人 寡妇 孤儿..
the bodies, the widows, the orphans...
这些是确定的
they were certain.
没人争议 人确实死了
Nobody disputed it, the
dead people were dead.
但战争的正当性却有很大争议
But the rectitude of the
war was in great dispute.
有权势的聪明人
Smart people in pinstripes
没能对战争作出对的决定
couldn't make their minds up about the war.
斯图亚特.赫林顿：我记得曾自问..
And I remember asking myself...
“这值得吗？”
"Was it worth it?"
也许这是个大错
Maybe it was all a big
mistake, and, you know,
这一切都为了什么？
what, what was it all about?
我们响应征召
We answered the call,
我和大约250万美国青年
me and probably 2 1/2 million
other young Americans
去了那里
who went over there.
这是个值得付出的理由
It was a cause worth the effort.
有时候 事情只是不遂人愿
And sometimes, things just don't turn out
而好人没赢
and the guys in the white hats don't win.
但这并不代表 嗯
But that doesn't make it, uh,
并不会从根本上剥夺
or doesn't basically take away
这理由的正当性
from the rectitude of the cause.
《第十集 往事如山》
下属委员会要求肃静
Subcommittee will come to order.
1973年的春天 夏天和秋天
NARRATOR: Night after night
during the spring, summer,
一个又一个夜晚
and fall of 1973,
美国人看着尼克松政府
Americans watched the Nixon administration
慢慢的解体
slowly come apart.
勒索
Blackmail,
敌人名单
enemies lists,
肮脏诡计
dirty tricks,
副总统被迫辞职
a vice president forced to resign,
伪证 掩盖证据
perjury, cover-up,
滥用总统权力
abuse of presidential power,
白宫秘密磁带
secret White House tapes.
弗雷德.汤普森：巴特菲尔德先生
FRED THOMPSON: Mr.
Butterfield, are you aware
你是否知道有录音设备
of the installation of
any listening devices
安装在总统的椭圆形办公室？
in the Oval Office of the president?
我知道录音设备
I was aware of listening devices.
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
晚上好
Good evening.
今晚美国可能处在历史上
The country tonight is in
the midst of what may be
最严重的宪法危机
the most serious constitutional crisis
之中
in its history.
我告诉总统这个情况
I told the president about the fact
有7名被定罪的被告
that there were money demands being made
有金钱要求
by the seven convicted defendants.
他问我要花多少钱
He asked me how much it would cost.
我告诉他 我只能估计
I told him I could only make an estimate
可能1百万美元或更多
that it might be as high as
a million dollars or more.
他告诉我没有问题
He told me that that was no problem.
我预先不知道水门闯入事件
I had no prior knowledge
of the Watergate break-in.
我既未参与也不知悉
I neither took part in nor knew about
任何随后的掩盖证据的活动
any of the subsequent cover-up activities.
杰克.托德：一件沮丧的事..
The one frustrating thing about...
关于去加拿大
about going to Canada was,
就是让我置身于辩论之外
it left me outside the debate here.
直到今天我还感到沮丧
I felt about... frustrated
with that till this day.
当水门丑闻被揭露时 杰克.托德
NARRATOR: As the Watergate
scandal unfolded, Jack Todd,
这个曾擅离美国陆军
who had deserted the United States Army
逃亡到加拿大的人
and fled to Canada,
他从未感到如此痛苦
had never felt so bitter,
如此幻灭 如此疏离
so disenchanted, so out of touch
面对变成这副模样的美国
with what the United States
seemed to have become.
他问自己“我们怎么让这帮人上台的？”
He asked himself, "How did we
let this gang take charge?"
然后他做了一个他会后悔一辈子的决定
Then he made a decision
he would always regret:
他放弃了美国公民身份
he renounced his American citizenship.
我认为这是个政治行为
JACK TODD: I thought it
was a political act,
放弃我的美国公民身份
renouncing my American citizenship.
这是我一生中最蠢的事
And it was the stupidest thing
I have ever done in my life.
我是个加拿大公民 我为此自豪
I'm a Canadian citizen and I'm proud of it.
这是个美好的国家 但在这里 我是美国人
It's a wonderful country, but
in here, I'm an American.
约翰.内格罗蓬特：那个协议叫作
JOHN NEGROPONTE: Well,
the agreement was called
“在越南结束战争
"The Agreement to End the War
和恢复和平的协议”
and Restore Peace in Vietnam."
当然 这是非常委婉的说法
And, of course, that was a huge euphemism.
它既没结束战争 也没恢复和平
It neither ended the war
nor did it restore peace.
如果看看它的实质
And if you look at the substance of it,
实际上是个撤军的协议
it really was a withdrawal agreement.
我们用撤离军队
We were withdrawing our forces
来换取战俘
in exchange for prisoners of war.
这两件事通过和平协议
Those are the two matters that
were definitively settled
得以最后解决
by the peace agreement.
我们让军队撤出 战俘回家
We got our troops out and
we got our prisoners back.
其余的部分都是典型的含糊不清
The rest is just all a model
of nebulosity and vagueness
没有解决任何事情
and didn't resolve a darn thing.
蓝光诗：美国人同意停火后
可以让14.5万北越部队留在南方
我们怎么能说这是个好的停火协议？
如果还有14.5万人留在我们国家？
停火后北越立即发起攻击
无论北方或南方
NARRATOR: Neither North nor South Vietnam
都没打算遵守
had had any intention of
observing the cease-fire
1973年1月27日在巴黎签订的
called for in the peace
treaty signed in Paris
呼吁停火的协议
on January 27, 1973.
甚至在协议墨迹未干时
Even before the ink was dry,
双方都试图尽可能多的抢占领土
each side had sought to claim
as much territory as it could
这被成为“旗帜之战”
in what became known as
"the War of the Flags."
停火3周内
Within three weeks of the ceasefire,
双方已有3000多起违规行为
there were already some 3,000
violations by both sides.
南越总统阮文绍
South Vietnamese President
Nguyen Van Thieu,
现在统帅世界上第5大的军队
who now commanded the
fifth-largest army on Earth,
他坚持要南越军占领和坚守每一寸领土
insisted the ARVN take and hold
every inch of South Vietnam,
即便这件事在近60万美军的帮助下
something they had been unable to do
他们都未能办到
even with the help of nearly
600,000 American troops.
（爆炸）
(explosion)
与此同时 北越军进攻
Meanwhile, the North Vietnamese
had attacked Tay Ninh,
靠近柬埔寨边境的西宁
near the Cambodian border,
希望在南方建立
hoping to establish a rival
capital of their own
自己的首都
in the South.
河内在非军事区下方的溪山附近
Hanoi installed surface-to-air
missiles near Khe Sanh,
安装地对空导弹
just below the DMZ.
同时 南越军攻击
At the same time, ARVN
troops attacked enclaves
北越夺取的飞地
seized by the North Vietnamese.
战斗进行了几个月
The fighting went on for months.
河内在南越境内
Hanoi built a new paved highway
修建了一条新马路
within South Vietnam itself,
200至300台车辆的护卫队
down which convoys of 200 to 300 vehicles
很快开始长驱直入
soon began streaming:
卡车、坦克和重型武器在白天移动
trucks, tanks, and heavy guns
moving in broad daylight.
他们着手铺设巨大油管
And they began laying
down a giant oil pipeline
用以在南方供应车辆燃料
to fuel their vehicles in the South.
尼克松私下向阮总统承诺
Nixon had privately
promised President Thieu
如果西贡受到严重威胁
that he would retaliate
with American airpower
他会使用美国空中力量报复
if Saigon ever seemed seriously threatened.
（槌击声）
(gavel banging)
但在华盛顿 一周又一周
But in Washington, week by week,
当水门的秘密接连涌现
as the secrets of Watergate
kept tumbling out,
尼克松对国会山的影响持续减弱
Nixon's influence on Capitol
Hill steadily weakened.
1973年6月 受刺激的国会
In June of 1973, an energized Congress,
回应多数美国人的观点
reflecting the views of a
majority of Americans,
投票决定停止在越南
voted to stop all military operations
老挝或柬埔寨的所有军事行动
in or over Vietnam, Laos, or Cambodia
截止时间为8月15日
by August 15,
并坚持没有国会的批准
and insisted that they not be resumed
行动不得恢复
without congressional approval.
“美国要和平”
"America wants peace,"
马萨诸塞州参议员爱德华.肯尼迪宣称
Senator Edward Kennedy of
Massachusetts declared.
“国会下定决心结束杀戮”
"Congress is strong in its
resolve to end the killing."
列维.索利：我们放弃南越
LEWIS SORLEY: To abandon
the South Vietnamese,
最后只提供资金支持
when all we were providing
them at the end was money,
是应该被谴责的行为
was reprehensible,
这是不尊重所有军人的牺牲
and disrespected the
sacrifices of all soldiers,
我们的和南越的
ours and the South Vietnamese.
我认为道德义务
I think the moral obligation,
不是源于阻止共产主义
that doesn't stem from a
philosophical commitment
的哲学承诺
to stopping communism.
现在是源于履行我们
Now it stems from our keeping our promises
对这个不幸的往昔盟友的承诺
to this erstwhile, unfortunate ally.
他们把我们当做盟友
That they had us as the ally
而另外一方有苏联
where the other guys had the Soviet Union
和共产主义中国
and communist China.
我想 大多数美国人
Most Americans, I think,
不想听到说共产党人
would not like to hear it
said that the communists
是比美国更忠实的盟友
were more faithful allies
than the United States.
但实际上就是如此
But that is, in fact, what the case was.
罗伯特.盖德：虽然有人遗憾 在某些方面
ROBERT GARD: While one regrets
that we pulled the rug out,
我们是釜底抽薪
in some respects,
我认为最终结果没有区别
I think the ultimate outcome
would've been the same.
如果我们继续下去 长期而言
Had we continued, it would have cost
可能会耗费更多人命
probably more lives in the long term
而结果不会改变
with no change in the outcome.
签署和平协议后的
NARRATOR: In the 18 bloody months
18个血腥的月份里
that followed the signing
of the peace accords,
南越的形势变得岌岌可危
South Vietnam's position became
more and more precarious.
但到了1974年夏天
But by the summer of 1974,
很少有美国人予以关注
few Americans were paying attention.
他们正盯着国内发生的事
They were riveted by what was
happening to their own country.
..全面和完整的调查
...to investigate fully and completely
是否有充分理由
whether sufficient grounds exist
让众议院
for the House of Representatives
行使其宪法权力
to exercise its constitutional power
弹劾理查德.尼克松
to impeach Richard M. Nixon,
美利坚合众国总统
president of the United States of America.
议长：丹尼尔森先生？-是
SPEAKER: Mr. Danielson? -Aye.
议长：兰格尔先生？-是
SPEAKER: Mr. Drinan? -Aye.
议长：丹尼尔森先生？-是
SPEAKER: Mr. Rangel? -Aye.
议长：乔丹女士？-是
SPEAKER: Ms. Jordan? -Aye.
议长：洛特先生？-不
SPEAKER: Mr. Lott? -No.
1974年7月27日
NARRATOR: On July 27, 1974,
众议院司法委员会建议
the House Judiciary Committee recommended
以滥用职权弹劾总统
that the president be impeached
for abusing his office.
8月9日 为避免弹劾
On August 9, rather than face impeachment,
尼克松成为美国历史上第一位
Richard Nixon became the first
president in American history
辞职的总统
to resign.
尼克松：永远记住
NIXON: Always remember,
别人也许恨你
others may hate you,
但那些恨你的人不会赢
but those who hate you don't win
除非你恨他们
unless you hate them,
那样你就毁了自己
and then you destroy yourself.
在西贡总统府
NARRATOR: At the presidential
palace in Saigon,
阮总统关上他的办公室门
President Thieu closed his office door
拒绝见任何人
and refused to see anyone.
他已经把南越的生存置于
He had staked South Vietnam's survival
尼克松的个人承诺之上
on Nixon's personal pledge
那就是北越的侵略会遭遇
that North Vietnamese
aggression would be met
重新出动的美国空军
by renewed American airpower.
新总统杰拉德.福特
Just a few days after the
new president, Gerald Ford,
搬进白宫没几天
moved into the White House,
国会就把尼克松承诺给西贡的
Congress cut in half the funds
军事和经济援助的
for military and economic assistance
资金削减了一半
Nixon had promised to deliver to Saigon.
南越形势继续恶化
Conditions in South Vietnam
continued to deteriorate.
随着美国军事存在消失
With the American military presence gone,
每5名民工中有1人失业
one out of every five
civilian workers was jobless.
物价飞涨
Prices soared.
杨文梅：美国人犯了很多错误
DUONG VAN MAI ELLIOTT: There were
many mistakes made by the Americans,
但最大的错误
but the biggest mistake
是建立了依赖感
was in creating the sense of dependency.
另一个错误是按他们自己的模样
建立了一支军队
Another mistake was in creating
an army in their own image,
一支习惯于打富人战争的军队
an army that was used to
fighting a rich man's war.
南越太穷了
And South Vietnam was too poor
无法维持那样的战争
to be able to sustain that kind of war.
阮文绍的独裁主义持续增长
NARRATOR: Thieu had steadily
grown more authoritarian,
关闭报纸 限制反对党
closing newspapers, restricting
opposition parties,
买卖政治和军事职位
selling political and
military appointments.
一个天主教徒和佛教徒的联盟指控他
A coalition of Catholics
and Buddhists charged him
破坏南越生活的各个方面
with corrupting every aspect
of South Vietnamese life,
要求他辞职
and demanded his resignation.
成千上万示威者
Thousands of demonstrators
涌入西贡街头
poured into the streets of Saigon.
同时 长期处于低收入的南越军队
Meanwhile, the chronically
underpaid South Vietnamese Army
进一步减薪
had its pay cut further.
它开始解体
It began to disintegrate.
每月逃兵多达2万人
As many as 20,000 men were
deserting each month,
多数回家是去帮助家人
most heading home to try to
help their families survive
度过这段艰难时期
in such hard times.
仍在坚持战斗的南越军人
Those ARVN who stood and fought
经常不得不放弃
often had to do so without
the sophisticated weaponry
美国人训练他们使用的先进武器
they'd been trained by
the Americans to use.
尼克松提供的许多装备
Much of the equipment Nixon had provided
不适合南方正在进行的战争
was ill-suited to the war
the South was now waging,
飞机缺乏训练有素的飞行员
aircraft for which there
were no trained pilots
或地面部队
or ground crews,
火炮和军车
artillery and military vehicles
没有备件
for which there were no spare parts.
美国国会不打算提供更多
And the U.S. Congress was
in no mood to provide more.
燃油不足
Fuel ran low.
弹药也是如此
So did ammunition.
很快中央高地的炮兵
Before long, artillerymen
in the Central Highlands
每天只能发射4发炮弹
could fire just four shells a day,
步兵每月仅限使用85发子弹
and infantrymen were limited
to 85 bullets a month.
每月1颗手雷和85发子弹
你怎么作战？
打完85发子弹 你没法再打
战败无法避免
1974年11月
NARRATOR: In November of 1974,
河内政治局和中央军委
the Politburo and the Central
Military Committee met in Hanoi
开会讨论策略
to discuss strategy.
有些成员要求谨慎行事
Some members urged caution.
他们担心如果他们
They worried that if they tried
压迫西贡使其崩溃太快
to push Saigon to the point
of collapse too quickly,
美国人会回来
the Americans would return.
最终的胜利 他们估算会在1976年
Final victory, they calculated,
would come in 1976.
党的第一书记黎笋不同意
Party First Secretary Le Duan didn't agree.
“美国人已经离开了”他说
"Now that the United States
has pulled out," he said,
“他们很难再回头”
"it will be hard for them to jump back in."
他下令进行试探性攻击
He ordered a test attack
看看美国人是否会动用空中力量干预
to see if the Americans would
intervene with airpower
如同2年半以前的
as they had during the Easter Offensive
复活节攻势那样
2 1/2 years earlier.
（炮声）
(artillery fire)
1974年12月
In December 1974,
北越军进攻西贡东北的
North Vietnamese forces
attacked Phuoc Long,
福隆省
northeast of Saigon.
3个星期内他们占领了整个省
Within three weeks, they had
overrun the entire province
打死或俘获数千名南越守军
and had killed or captured
thousands of ARVN defenders.
美国没有任何回应
The United States did nothing in response.
福特总统专注于其他问题
President Ford, preoccupied
with other problems...
通货膨胀 失业 中东局势
inflation, unemployment,
tensions in the Middle East...
举行了一场未能
held a press conference
给南越人带来安慰的新闻发布会
that offered the South
Vietnamese no comfort.
你是否考虑除了补给之外
REPORTER: Are you considering
采取任何额外的措施
any additional measures,
beyond a supplemental,
来援助南越政府？
of assistance to the South
Vietnamese government?
此刻我不预先考虑
I am not anticipating
除补给之外的任何
any further action beyond that supplemental
进一步行动
at this time.
华盛顿似乎没兴趣
NARRATOR: Washington
seemed to have no interest
履行尼克松多次
in fulfilling the secret pledges
对阮文绍作出的秘密承诺
Nixon had repeatedly made to Thieu.
他目瞪口呆
He was stunned.
斯图尔特.赫林顿：随着共产旗帜
STUART HERRINGTON: With the communist flag
飘扬在西贡北边的一个省会上空
planted in a provincial capital
just to the north of Saigon,
对我而言 预示着厄运临头
to me, the handwriting was on the wall.
I then communicated with
我于是联系家人 告诉他们
my family, and told them
尽管我的服务期应该到8月
that even though my tour was
supposed to take me till August,
但我很快就会回家
that I would be home sooner.
我开始悄悄的 每次一小箱
And then I began to quietly,
one little box at a time,
把我的物品寄出越南
mail my possessions out of Vietnam.
（齐柏林乐队“克什米尔”）
("Kashmir" by Led Zeppelin playing)
北越现在发起
NARRATOR: The North
Vietnamese now undertook
对中央高地城市新的攻击
a new assault on cities
in the Central Highlands,
包括邦美蜀
including Ban Me Thuot,
在那里他们的军力相较过于分散的南越军
where their forces outnumbered
the over-extended ARVN
大约是6:1
nearly six to one.
邦美蜀在两天内陷落
Ban Me Thuot fell in two days.
詹姆斯.威尔班克：这是第2个省份失陷
JAMES WILLBANKS: And here is
the second province to fall,
丢得相当快
and it falls fairly quickly.
那个时候 他们意识到
At that point, they realize,
“我们不必等到1976年
"Well, we don't have to wait till 1976,
我们现在就能拿下”
we can go for it now."
河内很高兴
NARRATOR: Hanoi was delighted
美国人没什么反应
by the Americans' lack of response.
但之前黎笋发动的所有攻势..
But all the previous offensives
Le Duan had set in motion...
在1964年
in 1964,
1968年
in 1968,
1972年
in 1972...
都以失败告终
had ended in failure.
这次他求助于武元甲将军
This time, he turned to
General Vo Nguyen Giap,
对法国人的奠边府大捷
the architect of the great
victory over the French
的缔造者
at Dien Bien Phu,
他在春节攻势期间被打入冷宫
who had been sidelined
during the Tet Offensive.
韦德：黎笋认识到他需要良将
来取得战争的胜利
总部的行动表明 从那以后
武元甲大将在全面指挥战争
几周里 南越军队高层
NARRATOR: For weeks, the ARVN top command
警告阮文绍 他让已经孱弱的部队
had warned Thieu that his
already weakened forces
分布得太稀疏
were spread too thinly;
无法保卫整个国家
that it was no longer possible
to defend the entire country.
他生气的反对
He had angrily resisted.
但现在 突然间他改变主意
But now, suddenly, he changed his mind.
阮命令部队放弃高地
Thieu ordered his troops
to abandon the highlands,
火线撤退
to withdraw under fire
然后重新集结 夺回邦美蜀
and then regroup in order
to retake Ban Me Thuot.
即便仔细的制订计划 那也是
It would have been a near-impossible task
一个近乎不可能完成的任务
with a carefully worked-out plan.
阮文绍什么都没有
Thieu had none.
（枪声）
(gunfire)
（爆炸）
(explosion)
结果是场灾难
The result would be disaster.
范唯必：这是个混乱局面
不恰当命令发出
致使混乱
最终 一切分崩离析
一周之内
NARRATOR: Within a week,
波来古和昆嵩落入敌手
Pleiku and Kon Tum were in enemy hands.
保宁：30年没有结果的战争
我们突然意识到
可以打下西贡
即使我这样的普通士兵都能看出来
据西贡的西方外交官说
According to Western
diplomats here in Saigon,
南越人正退出中央高地
the South Vietnamese are
quitting the Central Highlands
因为他们希望避免一场完全的溃败
because they hope to avoid a complete rout.
撤退据说是尝试
The withdrawal is said to be an attempt
保留即将奇缺的人员和装备
to save men and equipment
that may become sorely needed
用于其他人口较多的地区
in other, more heavily populated
parts of the country.
范唯必：阮总统下令
遗弃平民和当地部队
大家看到军队撤退
听说越共要来
他们惊慌逃跑
很多军人还带着家属
他们也不得不逃离
当南越军南逃时
NARRATOR: As the ARVN fled south,
40万平民跟着他们逃跑
400,000 civilians fled with them.
敌人阻断了主要道路
The enemy blocked the main roads
这样他们不得不走废弃的小道
so that they had to take
a disused back road.
数千人死亡
Thousands died,
死于北越炮弹
killed by North Vietnamese shells
和机关枪
and machine gun fire,
被同行的难民践踏
trampled by fellow refugees,
被撤退的坦克碾压
run over by retreating tanks,
被南越飞行员误判为敌人
blown apart by South Vietnamese bombs
扔下的炸弹炸碎
dropped by pilots who
mistook them for the enemy.
记者称之为“哭泣的车队”
Reporters called it the "Convoy of Tears."
接着顺化陷落
Then, Hue fell.
我们直奔顺化
解放顺化后朝岘港前进
傀儡军队丢弃军服溃逃
1975年3月29日
NARRATOR: On March 29, 1975,
北越进入岘港
the North Vietnamese entered Danang,
南越第二大城市
South Vietnam's second-largest city.
平民和士兵都在设法逃跑
Civilians and soldiers alike tried to flee.
（人群嘈杂声）
(crowd clamoring)
“岘港不是被打下的”一位美国记者记得
"Danang was not captured," an
American reporter remembered.
“而是崩溃于自己的恐慌”
"It disintegrated in its own terror."
（飞机发动）
(plane engine starting)
黎明闺：攻占后我们去了岘港
分派给我的房子原属一个南越军官
行李放在房子中间 他们没拿
我走进一个小房间
他女儿裁剪下一套衣服
但没有完成
邻居后来说这家人坐驳船逃跑
驳船把他们送去大船
但驳船沉了 他们都死了
晚上我很害怕在屋里
我想他们的鬼魂会回来
我好害怕 要朋友和我一起住
差不多10年前美国陆战队
NARRATOR: On the same beach
where the U.S. Marines
登陆的同一片海滩
had landed nearly ten years earlier,
美国开始卷入越战的地方
beginning America's combat
involvement in Vietnam,
1万6千名南越士兵
16,000 ARVN soldiers fought for space
与7万5千名惊慌的平民争先恐后的
with 75,000 terrified civilians
登上由货船和渔轮组成的船队
aboard an improvised fleet of
freighters and fishing boats
向南驶往金兰湾 头顿和西贡
headed south for Cam Ranh
Bay, Vung Tau, and Saigon;
任何他们认为北越军不会追赶的地方
anywhere they thought Northern
troops might not follow.
数千人在抢着上船时被淹死
Thousands drowned struggling
to reach the boats.
数千人被雨点般落下的
Thousands more were killed by enemy shells
炮弹炸死在海滩上
raining down on the beach.
胡友兰：傀儡军队在逃跑
之前 我们打一年仗用一张地图
到了75年我们每天换地图
一天的进展超过20年
岘港 三歧
NARRATOR: Danang, Tam Ky,
广义 归仁
Quang Ngai, Qui Nhon,
芽庄 金兰湾
Nha Trang, Cam Ranh Bay.
北越军持续进军越来越
The North Vietnamese kept
moving closer and closer
接近西贡
to Saigon.
坐在西贡让人惊惶失措
It was stunning to sit there in Saigon,
写着新闻头条
writing the daily ledes
这些地方接连沦陷
on the fall of all these places.
你就像淹没在
You just were overwhelmed
10年来的历史航程里
with ten years' worth of history
眼看着一切走向崩溃
and seeing all of it come unglued.
（爆炸）
(explosion)
弗兰克.斯奈普：3月底
FRANK SNEPP: At the end of March,
18个北越师
18 North Vietnamese divisions,
会同5个预备师
with five in reserve,
集结起来
were now arrayed
和差不多6个南越师对峙
against, basically, six
South Vietnamese divisions.
兵力不平衡
The manpower imbalance
约3比1或4比1，共军占优
was about three or four to one,
in favor of the communists.
真是惊心动魄
This was breathtaking.
北越现在决定
NARRATOR: The North Vietnamese now decided
朝西贡进军
to move against Saigon
在5月19日胡志明生日之前拿下
and take it before Ho Chi
Minh's birthday on May 19.
中情局西贡站站长
It became clear to Thomas Polgar,
托马斯.波尔加心中明白
the C.I.A. station chief in Saigon,
到了该准备撤离的时候
that the time had come to begin
preparing for an evacuation.
西贡还有约5千名美国人
There were still some 5,000
Americans in Saigon,
还有多达20万
and there were also as many
和美国合作过的
as 200,000 South Vietnamese
and their families
南越人及家属
who had cooperated with the United States.
但格拉汉姆.马丁大使不同意
But Ambassador Graham Martin disagreed.
他是个坚定的冷战斗士
He was a resolute Cold Warrior,
任命他 意在打消阮文绍
who had been appointed to reassure Thieu
对于美国继续支持的疑虑
of continuing American backing,
他儿子在越南的死亡
and his feelings had only been intensified
只能加剧他的这种感觉
by the death of his son in Vietnam.
他曾告诉一位助手
He had not been appointed ambassador,
他被任命为大使
he had told an aide,
不是要把“越南交给共产党人”
to "give Vietnam away to the communists."
他说中情局危言耸听
The C.I.A. was being alarmist, he said.
西贡不会受到任何攻击
There would be no attack on Saigon,
所以不必撤离
and, therefore, no evacuation.
阮文绍总统也坚持还有希望
President Thieu also continued
to insist all was not lost.
南越军准备“战斗到最后一颗子弹
The ARVN were ready to
"fight on to the last bullet
和最后一粒米” 他说
and the last grain of rice," he said.
距西贡以东仅40公里
Just 40 miles east of Saigon,
北越军队攻击
North Vietnamese forces attacked
1号公路上的春禄镇
the town of Xuan Loc on Highway One,
这是通往西贡的最后障碍
the last obstacle on their way to Saigon.
尽管北越兵力和武器占优
Although they were
outnumbered and outgunned,
南越指挥官坚守不退
the South Vietnamese commander
refused to retreat.
他决心把敌人拒于首都之外
He was determined to keep
the enemy from his capital.
记者：你确定能守住春禄？
REPORTER: You're certain
that you can hold Xuan Loc?
当然 当然
Surely, surely.
我向你保证
I am certain to you.
我向你保证 我会守住春禄
I am sure with you I can hold Xuan Loc.
即使敌人用上
Even the enemies uses, you
know, the double forces
双倍乃至三倍于我的兵力
or maybe three time more than my forces.
但没有问题 先生
But no problem, sir.
没有问题
No problem.
福特：一场巨大的人类悲剧
FORD: A vast human tragedy
已经降临在我们越南和柬埔寨的朋友身上
has befallen our friends
in Vietnam and Cambodia.
4月10日
NARRATOR: On April 10,
福特总统在国会联席会议上
President Ford appealed to a
joint session of Congress
呼吁向西贡紧急援助
for emergency aid to Saigon.
如果他们拒绝 而西贡陷落
If they refused and Saigon fell,
应由国会而非白宫承受责难
Congress, not the White
House, should take the blame.
在5位总统和12届国会之下
Under five presidents and 12 Congresses,
美国介入印度支那
the United States was engaged in Indochina.
数百万美国人服役
Millions of Americans served,
数千人丧命
thousands died,
更多人受伤 被俘或失踪
and many more were wounded,
imprisoned, or lost.
总统向国会请求7.22亿美元
NARRATOR: The president asked
Congress for $722 million
用于军事援助
in military aid.
没人鼓掌
There was no applause.
大多数议员和他们的选民
Most legislators, and their constituents,
认为已经太晚 无力回天
thought it was too late
to make any difference.
最后国会投票反对任何军事援助
In the end, Congress voted
against any military aid.
裴严：我不认为象美国这样的大国
BUI DIEM: I didn't think that it is good
这么做是对的
for a big nation like the U.S.
to behave like that.
因为那个时候
Because by that time,
我们没要求美国士兵流血
we didn't ask for the blood
of American soldiers.
到了最后一刻 他们撒手不管了
I mean, the last minute, they
washed their hands like that.
作为一名外交官不该用过激言语
It is not up to a diplomat
to use strong words
来指责美国
against the American,
但我深感遗憾
but I felt deeply sorry about it.
斯奈普：我们打破一切规章制度让人们逃走
SNEPP: We broke every rule in
the book to get people out,
年轻官员在这么干
the young officers did,
但大使继续阻碍
while the ambassador continued to stonewall
使馆和华盛顿的行动
both the embassy and Washington.
撤离计划终于制订
NARRATOR: Evacuation plans
were finally drawn up.
有4个选项
There were four options:
西贡港停泊的货轮海运
sealift by cargo ships anchored
in the port of Saigon,
商业客机空运
airlift by commercial airliner,
军机空运
a military airlift,
最后一个手段
and, as a last resort,
是用直升机撤离到
evacuation by flights of helicopters
位于南中国海的
to a flotilla of U.S. Navy ships
一支美军小型舰队上
in the South China Sea.
马丁大使仍然兴趣不大
Ambassador Martin continued
to show little interest.
他说 美国要放弃南越
The slightest sign that the United States
哪怕是最轻微的迹象
would abandon South Vietnam, he said,
也会在大街上产生恐慌
would produce panic in the streets.
（炮声和爆炸）
(gunfire and explosions)
4月21日
On April 21,
春禄最终落入北越手中
Xuan Loc finally fell to
the North Vietnamese.
南越军浴血奋战了12天
The ARVN had valiantly held
on for 12 bloody days.
通往西贡的1号公路已经敞开
Highway One was now open
all the way to Saigon.
那天晚上 阮文绍总统辞职
That evening, President Thieu resigned.
4天后 中情局把阮文绍秘密带往台湾
Four days later, the C.I.A.
would spirit Thieu to Taiwan,
在那里一名美国使者给他带来
where an American emissary brought him
福特总统的私人讯息
a private message from President Ford.
现在不是他访问美国的好时机
It was not a good time for
him to visit America.
反战情绪高涨
Antiwar feelings were too strong.
“成为美国的敌人很容易”
"It is so easy to be an enemy
of the United States,"
阮文绍说
Thieu said,
“但成为朋友很难”
"but so difficult to be a friend."
阮文绍辞职的新闻
News of Thieu's resignation
使得数千名恐慌的越南人
had sent thousands of panicked Vietnamese
朝着新山一机场狂奔
rushing to Tan Son Nhut Airport,
希望逃离他们的国家
hoping to get out of their country.
有些人有出境签证 很多人没有
Some had exit visas; many did not.
陆战队尽力维持秩序
Marines did what they
could to establish order.
军士长胡安.瓦尔迪兹是负责
Master Sergeant Juan Valdez was
the noncommissioned officer
西贡陆战队警卫分队的士官
in charge of Marine Corps
Security Guards in Saigon.
他是1965年在越南
He had been one of the first Marines
登陆的首批陆战队员之一
to land in Vietnam in 1965.
瓦尔迪兹：人们试图贿赂陆战队员
VALDEZ: People were trying
to bribe the Marines.
他们拿着钱和珠宝
You know, they were bringing
money out there, jewelry,
想要离开这个国家
to get them out of the country.
我想大概门口的每一位陆战队员
I think just about every
Marine that was at the gate
都遇到过这种贿赂
encountered this type of bribes.
但他们不得不拒绝他们 是的 是的
But they had to refuse them, yeah, yeah.
杨文梅的家人
NARRATOR: Duong Van Mai Elliott's family
1954年逃离河内
had fled Hanoi in 1954,
把她姐姐棠留下来
leaving behind her older sister, Thang,
她后来加入了胡志明的部队
who had joined Ho Chi Minh's forces.
现在 20年过去
Now, 20 years later,
随着北越军逼近西贡
with the North Vietnamese
closing in on Saigon,
他们再次面临
they were faced with the prospect
将要逃亡的命运
of fleeing once again.
杨文梅：我妈妈不想离开
DUONG VAN MAI ELLIOTT: My
mother didn't want to leave.
她说不想再次成为难民
She said she didn't want
to be a refugee again.
她当了太多次难民
She had been a refugee too many times.
另外 我姐姐棠快要来了
Plus, my sister Thang was about to arrive
经过这么多年和我们重逢
and meet us after all these years.
她说她想留下来见棠
She said she wanted to stay and see Thang.
我父亲决定离开
My father was determined to leave,
因为他害怕 留下会被杀掉
because he was afraid that if
we stayed, we'd be killed.
他生我母亲的气 他们争吵
He got mad at my mother, and they argued,
但最后我母亲让步了
but in the end, my mother yielded
他坚持我们应该离开
to his, uh, insistence that we should...
they should leave.
潘全慧：我知道大势已去
PHAN QUANG TUE: I knew that
the end was approaching.
当你处于风暴的中心
When you are at the center of the storm,
你必须逃出去
you have to get out.
当我和我全家
When I myself and my immediate family,
我父亲和他全家
and my father and his immediate family,
去新山一机场
went to the Tan Son Nhut Airport,
经历了这一切我说 “真是疯了
through the whole thing I said,
"This is crazy, you know.
为什么 为什么我们要这样离开？”
Why, why do we have to leave
under these conditions?"
如此的耻辱
It was so humiliating.
我带着耻辱来到美国
And I carry that humiliation
with me to the United States.
当我排队登记找工作时
When I get in line to sign up for a job,
我是个..
you know, I was a...
我让他们想起越战
I remind them of the war in Vietnam,
美国人所痛恨的战争
which the Americans hate.
你只能这样失去国家和梦想
You have to lose a nation and a dream
感受..那种耻辱
to feel... to feel that humiliation.
阮圣松：我父母有9个孩子
8个儿子和我
我4个兄弟死在反法战争中
到我们胜利时 8个全都死了
我不想结婚
我的领导劝我
“如果你只关注打仗而没有后代
那将来我们的战士从哪儿来？”
幸运的是 我还是结婚了
有了两个儿子
他们长大后也参了军
然后在1975年
在我们接近胜利时
2月1日 我的两个孩子战死了
玛丽.克罗克：我们一直给阿灵顿
JEAN-MARIE CROCKER: We
have always sent a wreath
他的墓送花圈
to his grave at Arlington.
当然部分是怀念他
Partly in remembrance, of course, of him,
但想到如果其他伤心人也在那里
but also thinking, if other
grieving people are there,
或只是前去瞻仰的游客
or just people that are
visiting to pay their respects,
那会让他们了解到
that it's good for them
to know that people are,
这些军人仍被人怀念
that the soldiers are remembered.
福特：今天..
FORD: Today...
美国可以重拾
America can regain the sense of pride
在越南之前曾有的自豪感
that existed before Vietnam.
但它无法再打一场战争来实现
But it cannot be achieved
by refighting a war
对美国而言战争已经结束
that is finished as far
as America is concerned.
（掌声）
(applause)
（爆炸）
(explosion)
1975年4月27日
NARRATOR: On April 27, 1975,
火箭落在西贡的市中心
rockets landed in the heart of Saigon.
这是北越开始
It was the signal for the
North Vietnamese to begin
发起总攻的信号
their main assault on the city.
他们从5个方向攻击
They attacked from five sides,
他们的指挥官说“象一场飓风”
"like a hurricane," their commander said.
白宫下令美国货轮
The White House ordered
all American cargo ships
全部出海 而不必
to sail out to sea without waiting
等待搭载任何乘客
to take on any passengers.
有组织的海上运输已经不可能
There now could be no organized sealift.
（吉米.亨德里克斯“沿着瞭望塔”）
(Jimi Hendrix Experience's "All
Along the Watchtower" playing)
当共产党人开始炮击
NARRATOR: When the
communists began shelling
位于西贡东南的海滨小镇头顿
the seaside town of Vung Tau,
just southeast of Saigon,
成千上万惊恐的人
thousands of terrified people
爬上能找到的一切船只
clambered into any vessel they could find
希望被美国人搭救
in hope of rescue by the Americans.
大逃亡结束前
Before the exodus ended,
有超过6万来自头顿的
more than 60,000 refugees from Vung Tau
难民获救
would be picked up.
但还有数千人被落下
But thousands more were left behind,
绝望的在海上漂浮
floating helplessly at sea.
在美国大使馆
At the American Embassy,
马丁大使给亨利.基辛格
Ambassador Martin cabled Henry Kissinger,
现任国务卿发电报
now secretary of state,
“这是此间高级官员
that "It is the unanimous opinion
“的一致意见
"of the senior personnel here
不会有针对西贡的直接或严重的攻击”
that there will be no direct
or serious attack on Saigon."
斯奈普：许多人开始怀疑
SNEPP: A lot of us began to wonder
他是否失去了对现实的把握
whether he had lost grip on reality.
他在最后的日子里染上肺炎
He had come down with
pneumonia in the final days.
他极度衰弱
He was terribly enfeebled.
这也许影响了他的判断
And it's possible this
affected his judgment.
制订撤离计划的人悄悄指定
NARRATOR: Evacuation planners
had quietly designated
大使馆内两个地点
two spots within the embassy
作为潜在的直升机着陆区
as potential helicopter landing zones...
一个庭院可容纳大型直升机
a courtyard that could
accommodate large choppers,
和使馆屋顶的直升机停机坪
and the helipad on the embassy roof,
用于较小的机型
meant for smaller ones.
一棵老酸角树长在庭院中央
An old tamarind tree stood in
the center of the courtyard.
陆战队一再要求马丁大使
Again and again, the Marines
asked Ambassador Martin
允许砍掉它
for permission to cut it down
以免干扰起飞和降落
so as not to interfere with
the lift-offs and landings
他们确信这事迫在眉睫
they were certain would soon have to begin.
他一直拒绝
He always refused.
他说那棵树是美国决心的象征
That tree was a symbol of
American resolve, he said.
砍倒它会传递错误的信息
Cutting it down would
send the wrong message.
与此同时 杨文明将军
Meanwhile, General Duong Van Minh,
12年前曾参与
who had been part of the coup
推翻吴庭艳总统的政变
that overthrew President
Diem 12 years earlier,
宣誓成为南越新任总统
was sworn in as the new
president of South Vietnam.
他呼吁立即停火
He called for an immediate cease-fire
并要求美国人在24小时内离开
and asked that Americans
leave within 24 hours.
（爆炸）
(explosion)
4月29日凌晨3点58分
NARRATOR: On April 29,
at 3:58 in the morning,
北越的火箭弹纷纷坠落在
North Vietnamese rockets began falling
新山一机场
on Tan Son Nhut Airport.
北越就是..
The North Vietnamese were just...
把这些炮弹..
walking these shells...
这些巨大的130毫米炮弹发射到
these big 130-millimeter artillery shells
整个机场区域
all over the airfield,
基本上摧毁了跑道
destroying the runway, basically.
距离近到
It was close enough
你能听到炮弹飞过头顶
that you could hear the
incoming go overhead.
（呼啸声 爆炸）
(whistling, explosion)
两名陆战队卫兵
NARRATOR: Two Marine guards,
来自爱达荷州马歇尔敦的准下士达尔文.贾奇
Lance Corporal Darwin Judge,
of Marshalltown, Iowa,
和来自马萨诸塞州沃本的查尔斯.麦克马洪下士
and Corporal Charles McMahon,
Jr., of Woburn, Massachusetts,
死于炮击
were killed in the barrage...
这是最后一批在越南死去的美国军人
the last American servicemen
to die in Vietnam.
♪ 沿着瞭望塔..
♪ All along the watchtower...
瓦尔迪兹：我仍责怪大使
VALDEZ: I still blame the ambassador.
这不应该发生
This shouldn't have happened.
如果大使采取他理应采取的行动
You know, if the ambassador
had taken action
让人们离开那里
and gotten people out of there,
which he was supposed to,
这根本就不会发生
this would have never happened.
跑道密布弹坑
NARRATOR: The runways were cratered
堆满飞机残骸
and blocked by wrecked planes,
遍地是丢弃的炸弹和燃料箱
littered with jettisoned
bombs and fuel tanks.
美国人撤离的选项已所剩无几
The Americans had run out
of evacuation options.
是时候从海上舰队
It was time to call in the helicopters
调用直升机了
from the offshore fleet.
没有办法
There was no way
把剩下的越南人
all of the remaining South Vietnamese
全部撤走
could be evacuated.
（电锯声）
(chain saws buzzing)
使馆院内的酸角树
The tamarind tree in the embassy compound
终于被砍倒
was finally hacked down
这样可以让直升机着陆
so helicopters could begin landing.
瓦尔迪兹：他们不得不把大酸角树砍倒
VALDEZ: So they had to chop
this big tamarind tree down,
切成一段段拖走
cut it in pieces, tow it away.
然后还要请消防部门
And then they had to get
the fire department
清理所有碎片和杂物
to wash all the debris and everything
这样直升机降落时
so when the choppers land,
不会把这些碎片
they wouldn't suck up all those debris
吸进发动机
into the, uh, into the engines.
上午11点刚过
NARRATOR: Just after 11:00 a.m.,
首都一个特别电台
a prearranged signal to
evacuate was broadcast
广播预先安排的撤离信号
over a special radio
frequency in the capital:
“西贡气温105度 还在上升”
"The temperature in Saigon
is 105 degrees and rising."
（田纳西.福特“白色圣诞节”）
("White Christmas" by
Tennessee Ernie Ford playing)
♪我梦见..
♪ I'm dreaming...
接下来应该是宾.克劳斯贝
NARRATOR: It was supposed to
be followed by Bing Crosby
演唱的“白色圣诞节”
singing "White Christmas."
但电台DJ找不到录音带
But the disc jockey
couldn't find the record
只好播放了田纳西.福特的版本
and played Tennessee Ernie
Ford's version instead.
美国人和有合法文件的越南人
Americans and Vietnamese with proper papers
在预先安排的地点集合
gathered at pre-arranged collection points
登上巴士车队
and boarded convoys of buses.
当他们穿过拥挤街道去机场时
Angry South Vietnamese beat
on the sides of the vehicles
愤怒的越南人敲打着
as they moved through the crowded streets
车子两侧
to the airport.
报道西贡陷落的菲利普.卡普托
Philip Caputo, now covering
the fall of Saigon,
在撤离者中间
was among the evacuees.
菲利普.卡普托：我们从新山一空军基地撤离
PHILIP CAPUTO: We were evacuated
from Tan Son Nhut Air Base.
但开车穿过使馆时 你能看见那里的混乱
But we drove past the embassy,
and you just saw this scrum,
一大群人挤压在墙上
this horde of people pressing
up against the walls,
陆战队员站在墙上
and Marines standing on the wall
拿枪对着人群
and gun-butting people
to, uh, to keep them...
以阻止他们翻越围墙
to keep them from pouring over the walls.
机场的撤离人员分成
NARRATOR: The evacuees at
the airport were divided
50人一组搭直升机
into helicopter teams of 50 each,
并沿着一条长走廊前往停机坪
and led down a long hallway to the tarmac.
卡普托一组里有人开玩笑
Someone in Caputo's group joked
终于看到“隧道尽头的光亮”
about finally seeing "light
at the end of the tunnel."
直升机起飞了
The choppers take off.
它们飞向海岸
And they're flying, uh...
flying toward the coast.
你向下可以看到一切
And you could look down
and all you could see,
西贡四周 机场四周
all around Saigon, all around the airfield,
全是炮弹爆炸造成的
were just these plumes of
smoke from burning buildings,
建筑物燃烧的烟雾
from exploding artillery shells.
我永远不会忘记飞越海岸线的情景
And I'll never forget going
over that coastline,
看到整支第七舰队..许多的船..
seeing the entire 7th
Fleet... dozens and dozens...
那支巨大的舰队出现在那里
and this enormous fleet
out there like that.
我完全记得那种难以置信的感觉
And I just remember this sense
of, of disbelief, completely.
难以置信 同时又深感安慰
Disbelief and relief at the same time.
瓦尔迪兹：有1到1.2万人
VALDEZ: There were anywhere
from 10,000 to 12,000 people
来自四面八方围住使馆
surrounding the embassy.
我们想让美国人离开那里
We're supposed to get
Americans out of there.
我们还想让为我们工作的
And we were supposed to
get South Vietnamese
南越人进入使馆
that worked for us in the embassy.
中情局在我们身后
The C.I.A. was behind us,
他们指认
and they were pointing at the people
应该出来的人
who were supposed to get out.
但每次你伸手去抓指定的那个
But every time you reached out
to grab a specific individual,
其他人会抓住你的手
other people were grabbing your hands
试图把你拉下来
and trying to pull you
down with them, you know,
这样的话你可能会帮他们出来
so that you could help them out.
斯奈普：一些美国人走得如此仓促
SNEPP: Some Americans had left so rapidly,
他们把电台丢下来
they'd left the radios behind.
于是他们的越南朋友
So their Vietnamese friends
were on the radios
就在电台上呼救
begging to be rescued.
“我是韩 你的司机”
"I'm Han, the driver."
“我是玉先生 你的翻译”
"I'm Mr. Ngoc, your translator."
我意识到美国人在越南的惯常行为
I realized what the Americans
had often done in Vietnam.
他们忘了这些也是人类
They had forgotten that
these were human beings.
我在越南的经历
My experience in Vietnam
犹如开着一架B-52在高处投弹
had often been like a
B-52 strike from on high.
我不必面对这些行动的后果
I never had to confront the
consequences of my action.
我可以就那么让炸弹舱门开着
I could just let the bomb doors open
仍旧保持超然
and still remain detached.
使馆里别的地方
NARRATOR: Elsewhere in the embassy,
陆战队员疯狂的销毁机密文件
Marines frantically destroyed
classified documents.
瓦尔迪兹：屋顶有2个大焚烧炉
VALDEZ: The top of the roof
had two big incinerators
就在直升机停机坪下方
right underneath the helicopter pad.
陆战队焚烧机密文件
And the Marines burned classified material
争分夺秒
around the clock.
但据我了解 即使到我们离开时
But to my understanding, even when we left,
仍有机密资料留下
there was still classified
material left behind.
斯奈普：直升机最后到来时
SNEPP: Well, when the choppers
finally began coming in,
向下的气流撕开那些袋子
the downdraft ripped open those bags
机密资料在停车场上
and there was classified material
散落了一地
all over the parking lot.
北越人抵达时
When the North Vietnamese arrived,
显然他们只需用胶带把资料粘合
they apparently Scotch-taped
that material back together
就会成为一份杀戮名单
and it became a blood
list that they could use
用来追捕为我们工作的越南人
to track down people, Vietnamese,
who'd worked for us.
使馆官员把成袋的钞票
NARRATOR: Embassy officials
dumped bags of currency
倾进油桶
into an oil drum
并点着火
and set it afire.
几百万应急资金
Millions of dollars in contingency funds
化作烟尘
went up in smoke.
“这是西贡站最后的讯息”
"This will be the final
message from Saigon station,"
中情局站长波尔加给华盛顿发电报
the C.I.A. chief Thomas
Polgar wired to Washington.
“这是场漫长的战斗 而我们输了
"It has been a long fight and we have lost.
“那些未从历史中汲取教训的人
"Those who fail to learn from history
“被迫重复失败
"are forced to repeat it.
“我们希望不再有另一个越南的经历
"Let us hope that we will not
have another Vietnam experience
“我们已吸取教训
"and that we have learned our lesson.
西贡汇报完毕”
Saigon signing off."
50多架美国直升机
More than 50 U.S. helicopters
现在在西贡上空穿梭
now crisscrossed the sky over Saigon,
从指定的屋顶还有大使馆
picking up evacuees from
designated rooftops,
搭载撤离人员
as well as the embassy,
把他们运到远海的舰队上
ferrying them to the fleet far out at sea,
然后返回接更多人
then returning for more.
某些不顾一切的南越军官
Some desperate South Vietnamese officers
也为自己和家人
also commandeered helicopters
强行征用直升机
for themselves and their families,
铤而走险挤上
dangerously crowding the decks
美军航空母舰的甲板
of the American aircraft carriers.
并没有空间留给他们
There was no room for them.
威尔班克：我脑海里一直
WILLBANKS: The image
that remains in my mind
留存着直升飞机的画面
is the picture of the helicopter
从航母的一侧被推入大海
being pushed over the side of the carrier.
在越南直升机就是一切
The helicopter was everything in Vietnam.
我是说 它时刻待命 它补充给养
I mean, it was dust-off, it was resupply,
它是火力支援 它就是一切
it was fire support, it was everything.
我满脑子想的是 太浪费了
All I could think of was:
what a waste, what a waste.
当我目睹眼前的一切
As I watched that all unfold,
我深感自责
I, I felt responsible.
我很惭愧
I was ashamed.
我们告诉过这些人
We had told these people
我们会在那里支持他们
that we would be there to support them
而我们没有
and we were not.
斯奈普：最后一个晚上9点15分左右
SNEPP: About 9:15 on the last night,
波尔加过来说“我们都要离开了
Polgar came and he said,
"We've got to all leave.
“总部命令离开
"We've been ordered by
headquarters to leave.
我们走吧”
Let's go."
马丁大使想成为最后一个离开的人
NARRATOR: Ambassador Martin had
wanted to be the last man to leave.
但4月30日大约凌晨4点
But at about 4:00 in the
morning of April 30,
一架CH-46在使馆屋顶着陆
a CH-46 touched down on the embassy roof.
飞行员带着总统手令
Its pilot carried orders
from the president himself.
马丁现在就要离开
Martin was to leave, now.
“我想就是这样了”他说
"I guess this is it," he said.
当马丁被搀上飞机
As Martin was helped aboard,
他接过卷起的美国国旗
he was handed the furled American flag
这面旗帜前一天还在使馆旗杆上飘扬
that had flown from the
flagstaff the previous day.
他于凌晨4点59分起飞 直奔海上
He lifted off at 4:58 a.m.
and headed out to sea.
福特总统也下令从那时起
President Ford had also
ordered that from then on,
只撤离美国人
only Americans would be evacuated.
数以万计的南越人
Tens of thousands of South Vietnamese
会被遗弃
would be left behind,
400多人还在
and more than 400 were still waiting
使馆院内等待着
in the embassy courtyard.
他们一再被保证
Time and again, they had been assured
直升机正在接他们的路上
helicopters were on the
way to pick them up.
赫林顿：我被指示
HERRINGTON: I was directed
和越南人待在一起 让他们保暖
to stay with the Vietnamese
and keep them warm,
意思是“不要有任何暗示
meaning, "Don't give any hint
我们作出的所有承诺都是泡影”
that all these promises we
made to them are for naught."
我心里很难受 度过了一段艰难时刻
I felt sick at heart, I had a hard time.
天色很黑 所以我不必担心
It was dark out, so I didn't have to worry
直视这些人的眼睛
about looking these folks in the eye.
但我找了个借口（说越南语）..
But I made my excuse and,
um, (speaks Vietnamese)...
“我要去洗手间”
"I have to go to the bathroom."
离开后走进园林
And left into the landscaping,
迂回到大使馆后门
circuitous route to the
back door of the embassy,
到了使馆办公楼
to the chancery building,
径直上了屋顶
and made my way to the roof.
约有129名陆战队员还留在院子里
NARRATOR: Some 129 Marines
remained in the compound.
他们奋力
They did their best
撤进使馆 登上屋顶
to pull back into the embassy
and up onto the roof
没有惊动越南人
without alerting the Vietnamese
他们即将被遗弃
that they were about to be left behind.
瓦尔迪兹：我们把自己锁进大使馆
VALDEZ: We locked ourselves
inside the embassy
然后来到屋顶上
and found ourselves up on the roof.
其实上了屋顶以后
It was actually after we
got up on top of the roof
我们才看见庞大的人群
that we started seeing all
these masses of people.
有的已经进到使馆院内
Some of them had already come
on the embassy compound.
他们破坏了院门
And they broke those doors.
这样那些南越人
And that's how those, uh, South Vietnamese
得以进入使馆
were able to get inside the embassy.
罗恩.内森：这次行动是美国历史中一个章节的结束
RON NESSEN: This action closes a
chapter in the American experience.
总统要求全体美国人民紧密团结
The president asks all
Americans to close ranks,
避免对过去的互相指责
to avoid recriminations about the past,
为未竞的伟大事业
and to work together on the great tasks
而共同努力
that remain to be accomplished.
现在 告诉你们过去几天事情的细节
Now, to, uh, give you details of
the events of the past few days
回答你们问题的是
and to answer your questions,
国务卿基辛格
Secretary of State Kissinger.
记者：国务卿先生 你确信
REPORTER: Mr. Secretary, are you confident
所有想要离开的美国人
that all the Americans
that wanted to come out
都离开了西贡
are out of Saigon,
你是否知道
and do you have any idea
留下来的美国人的数量？
of the number of Americans
who remain behind?
我不知道留下的美国人的
I have no idea of the number of Americans
具体数字
that remain behind.
我确信每一个
Uh, I am confident that every American
想离开的美国人
who wanted to come out,
呃 都已离开
uh, is, is out.
我们国家现在要做的
What we need now in this country
是治愈创伤 让越南成为过去
is to heal the wounds and
to put Vietnam behind us.
一名助手递给基辛格一张纸条
NARRATOR: An aide handed Kissinger a note.
说有129名陆战队员
It said that the 129 Marines
不知何故还留在使馆屋顶
had somehow been left
behind on the embassy roof.
已经派出直升机去接他们
Helicopters were dispatched
to pick them up.
最后只有瓦尔迪兹军士
Eventually, only Sergeant Valdez
和他的10人使馆警卫队留下来
and his ten-man embassy
security unit remained.
但1小时过去
But then, an hour went by
再也没有直升机的动静
with no sign of any more helicopters.
他们的电台坏了
Their radio was dead.
陆战队没有办法联系舰队
The Marines had no way to contact the fleet
打听是否还有直升机在路上
to see if anyone was on the way.
瓦尔迪兹：一切都停止了
VALDEZ: Everything stopped.
我们滞留在那里
We're being left behind.
大家坐在那里胡思乱想
People are sitting around in
their own little thoughts,
都沉默不语
uh, not doing too much talking.
我们几乎决定要杀出去
We pretty much decided that we
were going to fight it out,
用手头现有的小型武器
use these small arms that we had
坚决战斗到底
and just fight it to the end.
这时我们看到海上出现两道烟雾
We started seeing two puffs of
smoke coming from out at sea.
随着越来越近 于是我们能确定
As they got closer, then
we were able to determine
它们是直升机
that they were helicopters.
真令人欣慰
It was a relief.
其中一位陆战队员 沙利文上士
One of the Marines, I believe
it was Staff Sergeant Sullivan,
我的助手
my assistant,
在收回舷梯时抓住我
grabbed me and started pulling me in
把我拉进去
as the ramp's going up.
1975年4月30日上午7:53
NARRATOR: At 7:53 a.m., April 30, 1975,
最后一架直升机飞离使馆屋顶
the last helicopter lifted
off the embassy roof.
军士长胡安.瓦尔迪兹
Master Sergeant Juan Valdez
是最后一位登上飞机的美国人
was the last American to climb aboard.
（警笛声）
(sirens wailing)
南越政府
The government of South Vietnam
只剩下5个小时的存活时间
had less than five hours to live.
杨文明总统上午在总统府发表讲话
President Minh spoke from
the palace at mid-morning.
他呼吁剩下的南越军队
He urged what was left of
the South Vietnamese Army
停止战斗
to stop fighting.
他说“我们等在这里 交出权力
"We are here waiting," he said,
"to hand over the authority
以避免无谓的流血”
in order to stop useless bloodshed."
保宁：如果杨文明没有下令投降
那就会很可怕
我们都得死
我有朋友在南越部队
咒骂杨总统
恨他是因为他下令投降
让越共赢得胜利
我在美国的朋友仍咒骂杨文明
但他们忘记了
如果他不下令
他们不会幸存下来去美国
并成为美国公民
他们会在西贡和我一起死去
范唯必：杨总统宣布投降时
我的私人指挥直升机还在
我还有一个飞行员
最终我决定不逃
我不得不接受现实
每个人都在谈论一场血洗
作为一名天主教徒我不能自杀
象很多人选择的那样
因此我接受自己的命运
中午时分
NARRATOR: At noon,
飘扬着越共旗帜的北越坦克
North Vietnamese tanks
flying Viet Cong flags
撞开总统府大门
smashed their way through the gates
闯了进去
of the presidential palace.
数小时内 胜利的士兵
Within hours, victorious soldiers
称西贡为“胡志明市”
were calling Saigon "Ho Chi Minh City."
全市的南越士兵脱掉制服
All over town, ARVN soldiers
tore off their uniforms
竭力混进人群
and did their best to melt into the crowds.
各家庭焚烧相册
Families burned their photo albums
这样就没有证据
so there would be no evidence
证明他们的儿子或丈夫为南越打过仗
that their sons or husbands had
ever fought for South Vietnam.
陈玉全上校12年里
Colonel Tran Ngoc Toan had
been fighting the communists
一直在和共产党打仗
for more than 12 years,
在平嘉战役中
and had survived terrible wounds
身负重伤存活下来
suffered at the Battle of Binh Gia.
他率领
He was leading what was left
南越陆战4营余部
of the 4th South Vietnamese
Marine Battalion
在边和附近 位于西贡以东20英里
near Bien Hoa, 20 miles east of Saigon.
他的上司将军早就
His commanding general had long since
贿赂上船逃离了国家
bribed his way aboard a
ship and fled the country.
一位美国朋友催促陈玉全也走
An American friend had urged
Toan to get out, too.
他拒绝了
He refused.
陈玉全：但我说 不
我不能抛弃我的国家
我尝试步行回西贡的家
我想死
当时我想很快死去
我不再想活下去
我想我的家人仍在那里
我的孩子分别是4岁和9岁
因此 想起他们 我继续步行回家
一位南越警长
NARRATOR: A South Vietnamese police officer
走到一座纪念保卫南越
walked to a memorial built to honor
牺牲的人的雕像前
those who had fallen
defending South Vietnam.
他向它敬礼 站了一会
He saluted it, stood there for a time,
然后朝自己头部开了一枪
and then shot himself in the head.
杨文梅：这是一场非常混乱的战争的
DUONG VAN MAI ELLIOTT: It
was a very messy ending
一个非常混乱的结局
to a very messy war.
当一切结束时我有种欣慰感
I felt a sense of relief,
但也有一种悲伤的感觉
but also a sense of sadness when it ended.
我觉得欣慰的是杀戮和破坏
I felt relief that the
killing, destruction,
最终走到结束
finally came to an end,
我不在乎哪边赢
and I didn't care which side won.
对于我 是越南赢了
To me, Vietnam won.
越南人民赢了
Vietnamese people won
因为他们最后终于能过上正常生活
because they finally could live normally.
悲伤的是我看到我的家人再次逃亡
And sad because I saw that
my family was again fleeing,
这次是逃离自己的祖国
and this time from their homeland,
他们前途未卜
and their future was very uncertain.
我知道共产党接管以后
And I knew that with the
communists taking over,
越南社会会发生剧烈变化
Vietnamese society would
be changed drastically.
鲁克心在北越军队里
NARRATOR: Lo Khac Tam had been fighting
打了差不多10年仗
in the North Vietnamese Army
for nearly ten years now,
始于德浪河谷的血战
beginning with the bloody
clash in the la Drang Valley,
那是美国参战后第一次全面战役
the first full-scale battle
of the American war.
现在他看到了战争的结局
Now he was watching that war's end.
鲁克心：我无法走上街头
我想起倒下的同志们
我活了下来
但我为失去他们而哭泣
无论何时我听到那首歌
“你走了 三次远走 再不归来”
我无法忍住自己的眼泪
因为我深爱死去的弟兄们
在越南 我们终于到达隧道尽头
In Vietnam, we finally have
reached the end of the tunnel,
而那里没有亮光
and there is no light there.
那里有的 也许正如福特总统所说
What is there, perhaps, was
best said by President Ford,
“一场已经结束的战争”
"a war that is finished."
列维.索利：我碰巧在
LEWIS SORLEY: I happened
to be at a conference
塔夫茨大学开会
at Tufts University,
那里的院长是前任大使
and the dean there was a former ambassador
当天晚上他给我们讲话
who spoke to us late on that day,
结果 那是命里注定的一天
as it turned out, the fateful day.
他说他刚从华盛顿回来
And he said he had just
come back from Washington,
那里春和景明
where the spring weather was beautiful
水仙花盛开
and the daffodils were in bloom,
到了波士顿就天色晦暗 如同他的内心
to Boston, where it was gloomy
and gray as it was in his heart.
人们就嘘他和起哄
And people hissed him and booed him.
我穿着制服
I was there in uniform.
我最大的遗憾就是没起身
One of my great regrets
was that I did not get up
去痛斥那些人
and start laying waste to those people
他们不尊重大使
who disrespected the ambassador
和他对南越陷落的痛心
and his sorrow at the
fall of South Vietnam.
马斯格雷夫：我接到一个
“越战老兵反战”全国办公室的电话
I got a call from the V.V.A.W.
national office
是些过去的老朋友
from some friends of
mine from the old days.
他们有个盛大的庆祝活动
They were having a big celebration,
开怀畅饮 说“这是个好日子 不是吗？”
drinking booze and, "Ah, well,
it's a great day, isn't it?"
我说“你有病吧？”
And I said, "Are you nuts?"
我说“这不是个好日子”
I said, "No, it's not a great day."
看到美国人象那样离开
To see America leaving like that,
历经近6万美国儿女捐躯之后
after we'd given almost 60,000
of our sons and daughters,
这不是什么值得庆祝的事情
that wasn't something to celebrate.
我知道我们正在抛弃
I knew we were abandoning
数百万信任我们
millions of South Vietnamese
that had trusted us,
和我们休戚与共的越南人
thrown in their lot with us.
这根本不值得庆祝
That wasn't anything to celebrate.
我想这是我在美国历史上
I thought it was just one
of the saddest moments
看到过的最悲哀的时刻
I'd ever seen in American history.
所以当未来某些政客 由于某种原因
So when some future
politician, for some reason,
觉得需要把国家拖入战争
feels the need to drag
this country into a war,
他可以来阿灵顿国家公墓
he might come out here to Arlington,
可以站在这里某个地方
and stand maybe right over there somewhere,
宣布他的决定 并说出他的想法
to make his announcement and
to tell what he has in mind.
越南战争持续了30年
从1945到1975年
我属于少数几个
能活着回家的人
打了6年仗后我走进家门
6年里没写过一封信
6年来我妈妈不知道我是死是活
你能想象出一个母亲该有多高兴？
战争让女性最悲惨
接着就是最高兴
我妈妈哭了 但我们没有抱头痛哭
越南人就这样
我妈妈马上想到我们的邻居
他家刚收到一封阵亡通知书
在我们这个楼里
有6个人应征
只有我回来了
但我们不敢庆祝
因为邻居家都失去了孩子
（掌声）
(cheering)
汤姆.瓦列雷：在越南 共产党欢庆胜利
TOM VALLELY: In Vietnam, the
Communist Party is triumphant.
但他们也有例外主义
And they have exceptionalism, too.
他们的例外主义是他们的阻碍
And their exceptionalism gets in their way
就像我们的例外主义是我们的阻碍
just like our exceptionalism
got in our way.
因此他们在军事意义上统一了国家
So they unify the country
in a military sense,
然而胜利后他们并没有真正统一
and then they, they don't really
unify the country after that.
他们尝试过 但他们失败了
They, they try, but they fail.
最后并没有出现
NARRATOR: In the end,
there was no bloodbath
很多人担心的大规模屠杀
on the scale many had feared,
但在农村 有数百乃至数千人
but hundreds, perhaps thousands,
of people in the countryside
据称死于
are thought to have been killed
个别复仇行为或政治报复
in individual acts of revenge
or political retaliation.
那些服务于阮文绍政权的人
Those who had served the Thieu regime,
从将军到普通文员
from generals to ordinary clerks,
被要求接受再教育
were required to undergo re-education.
当兵的人获悉
Enlisted men were assured
他们只需接受为期3天的“学习”
they would only have to submit
to three days of "study."
军官只需参加不超过1个月
Officers needn't attend
for more than a month.
范唯必：有人以为去的时间不会长
但我不这么认为
我在再教育营
待了7年半
我属于最后被释放的100人之列
韦德：提到去教育营 媒体说“去学习”
没人说过“去监狱”
据信有150万人
NARRATOR: A million and a half people
经历了不同形式的思想教化
are believed to have undergone
some form of indoctrination.
南越军人公墓被推平或上锁
ARVN cemeteries were
bulldozed or padlocked,
仿佛一个独立南越的记忆
as if the memory of an
independent South Vietnam,
以及那些为这个事业而死的人
and those who had died for that cause,
可以被一同抹去
could both be obliterated.
杨文梅：共产党人
DUONG VAN MAI ELLIOTT: The communists,
努力消除前政权
in their effort to erase vestiges
残留的痕迹
of the former regime,
不允许战争中
have not allowed the South Vietnamese
丧子的南越人
who lost their sons in the war
哀悼 建坟和纪念他们
to mourn, to have their graves
and to honor their memory.
造成的分裂延续至今
It caused a division
that lasts to this day,
胜利者容不下失败者
that the winners would not
accommodate the losers
某种程度上是这样
in some way.
阮玉：我们成了一个国家
但我要说的是
越南人民从未象今天这样分裂过
30年战争之后 越南许多地方是废墟
NARRATOR: After 30 years of war,
much of Vietnam lay in ruins.
据认为南北双方共有
Three million people are
thought to have died,
300万人死亡
North and South.
还有更多人受伤
Still more had been wounded.
数以千计的美国军人生下的孩子
Thousands of children fathered
by American servicemen
被遗弃在越南
had been left behind.
村庄需要重建 土地必须重整
Villages needed to be rebuilt,
land had to be reclaimed.
城市里充塞着难民
Cities were choked with refugees.
数百万人没有工作
Millions were without work.
福特总统实行经济禁令
President Ford imposed an economic embargo.
华盛顿拒绝承认越南新政府
Washington refused to recognize
the new government of Vietnam.
但黎笋和政治局的盟友们
But Le Duan and his allies on the Politburo
保持乐观
remained optimistic.
“不会再发生什么事”一位委员说
"Nothing more can happen,"
one committee member said.
“我们现在面临的问题
"The problems we face now are trifles
和过去相比微不足道”
compared to those in the past."
靠苏联的帮助 黎笋决心
Le Duan resolved, with Soviet help,
把整个越南变成他所说的
to turn all of Vietnam into what he called
一个“社会主义制度的坚强前哨”
an "impregnable outpost
of the socialist system."
河内在南方强推农业集体化
Hanoi forcibly collectivized
agriculture in the South,
事实上废除了资本主义
virtually abolished capitalism,
实行工业国有化
nationalized industries,
并指派计划人员严格
and appointed planners to run it all
按共产主义路线管理一切
along strict communist lines.
结果是经济灾难
The result would be economic disaster.
年通货膨胀率高达700%
Inflation rose as high as 700% a year.
人民忍饥挨饿
People starved.
保宁：战后10年最可怕
我们的生活标准完全崩溃
降到了最低点
那是绝对的可怕
战争期间 人们能接受艰难困苦
但战后
这是个巨大错误
斯大林主义经济政策的恶果
这是共产主义的经济问题
使这些问题更加严重的是
NARRATOR: To compound its problems,
越南发现自己再次因
Vietnam found itself, once again, at war,
两个共产强权之间的利益招致战争
caught between the interests
of the two communist powers
他们曾是其最坚定的盟友
that had once been its staunchest allies,
中国和苏联
China and the Soviet Union.
（枪声 叫喊）
(gunshot, man yells)
当粗暴的柬埔寨毛派政权
After the brutal Maoist regime in Cambodia
袭击边境地区之后
raided border areas,
越南军队在苏联人的武装和打气之下
Vietnamese troops, with Soviet
arms and encouragement,
于1978年越过边界推翻了它
crossed the frontier in
1978 and overthrew it.
一场令人沮丧的
A frustrating ten-year
为期十年的镇压运动接踵而至
counterinsurgency campaign followed
有人称之为“越南人的越南”
that some called "Vietnam's Vietnam."
运动结束时
Before it was over,
约有5万越南人死于非命
the Vietnamese would lose
some 50,000 more men,
几乎和死在越战的美国人一样多
almost as many as the Americans
had lost in their war.
（爆炸 炮声）
(explosions and gunfire)
与此同时 共产中国
Meanwhile, communist China,
决心惩罚越南入侵柬埔寨
determined to punish Vietnam
for invading Cambodia,
并向莫斯科展示它不能
and to show Moscow it would
not have a free hand
在东南亚不受约束
in Southeast Asia,
派出了8.5万人的部队闯入越南北部
sent 85,000 troops storming
into northern Vietnam.
在越南人把他们打回去之前
They devastated areas along the border
他们破坏了边境沿线
before the Vietnamese pushed them back.
艾德.布拉德利：1978年 南中国海
ED BRADLEY: The South China Sea, 1978.
他们以每月1万人的速度上岸
They come ashore at the
rate of 10,000 a month,
比美国和其他国家愿意接收的
much faster than the United
States or any other nation
速度要快得多
is willing to accept them.
他们来追逐一个飘忽的记忆：
They come chasing an elusive memory:
美国的承诺
the promise of America.
最终150万人逃离越南
NARRATOR: A million and a half people
would eventually flee Vietnam:
旧日西贡政权的支持者们
supporters of the old Saigon regime,
来自柬埔寨边境
refugees from the renewed fighting
重新开战地区的难民
along the Cambodian border,
遭受新政府严苛对待的
and ethnic Chinese residents of Vietnam,
越南华裔居民
whom the new government had
treated especially harshly.
成千上万的船民死亡
Hundreds of thousands of
the boat people died.
其他人在遍布东南亚的
Others suffered in refugee camps
难民营受苦
throughout Southeast Asia.
约有40万人最终到达美国
Some 400,000 eventually made it to America,
在那里他们被安置到几乎每个州
where they settled in nearly every state,
勤勤恳恳 艰苦创业
industrious, entrepreneurial,
比亚洲其他移民群体
more eager to take part in
American political life
更加渴望参与美国政治生活
and more likely to become American citizens
更愿意成为美国公民
than other immigrant groups from Asia.
但对于第一代越南裔美国人
But for that first generation
of Vietnamese Americans,
家园的记忆永远不会被抹去
memories of their homeland
could never be erased.
陈玉全：差不多30年过去了 我很幸福
我为自己和家庭作出了正确选择
尽管我希望能够回越南 死在那里
我想对我的孩子们说
“我想回越南了却余生”
但我没有这样的勇气
因为那样会伤害他们的感情
我不想让他们误解我
卡尔.马兰奇：我记得
KARL MARLANTES: I remember I was
我和一个女儿在一起..（笑）
with one of my daughters, uh... (chuckles)
在十字路口某人在我后面
at an intersection and
some guy came up behind me
按喇叭
and blasted the horn.
当我清醒过来时
When I came to my senses,
我站在他汽车的引擎盖上
I was on the hood of his car,
准备要踢他的挡风玻璃
about to, trying to kick his windshield in.
周围的人都在看着我
And I went... and there's
people all over looking at me.
我是说 真是疯了 真是疯了
I mean, this is crazy. This is crazy.
接着我开始觉得“这真是不可思议”
And then I started going,
"Well, this is weird."
我躲回自己车里
I sort of slinked back
to my car and, you know,
我的女儿 大概4岁 看着我
my daughter, she's about
four, looking at me,
“哇 这是怎么回事？”
"Wow, what's that all about?"
我也在想“这是怎么回事？”
And I go, "What is that all about?"
我不知道
I had no idea.
我不知道它是否与战争有关
I had no idea that it was
even related to the war.
它和战争本身一样古老
NARRATOR: It is as old as war itself.
古希腊人称之为“神圣的疯狂”
The ancient Greeks called
it "divine madness."
在南北战争中叫“士兵之心”
It was "soldier's heart" in the Civil War,
一次大战期间叫“炮弹休克症”
"shell shock" during the First World War
二战中叫“战斗疲劳症”
and "combat fatigue" in the Second.
之后的越南 它被赋予一个新的名字
Following Vietnam, it was given a new name,
创伤后应激障碍
Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder...
PTSD.
马兰奇：你懂得PTSD无法痊愈
MARLANTES: And what you learn
is that PTSD doesn't go away.
但现在如果有人按喇叭
But now if someone honks the horn,
还会吓我一跳
and it startles me, I'm still...
我的心率还会上升
My heart rate's still going to go up,
会持续5分钟 就是这样
and it'll be there for five
minutes and I'm like this.
但是“10 9 ..那只是某个混蛋
But, "Ten, nine, it's just some asshole,
“他今天工作不顺心..8 7 6
"he's had a bad day at
work, eight, seven, six,
“没人朝你开枪 你很安全
"it's not... no one's
shooting at you, you're safe,
7 6 5 4 3 2 1”
it's seven, six, five,
four, three, two, one."
于是我能控制自己了
And I can control it,
然而以前我做不到
whereas I couldn't do it before
因为我不明白是怎么回事
because I didn't understand
what was going on.
让很多老兵痛苦加深的
NARRATOR: Adding to the
pain many veterans felt
是他们的国家急于忘掉这场战争
was their country's eagerness
to forget the war.
几乎没有列队欢迎
There were few parades.
每个人从越南各走各路 独自回家
In many ways, everyone came
home from Vietnam alone.
我回到家时
When I got home,
我爸妈在那里
and my mom and dad were there,
我的兄弟姐妹 我的妻子
my brothers and sisters, my wife.
我们拥抱和..
And we're embracing and...
我不能跟我的妻子或母亲谈到
I couldn't relate to my wife
or my mother what I had seen,
在越南的所见所为
what I had done in Vietnam.
我能跟兄弟们谈论这些
I could've talked to my brothers about it,
但他们知道我不想谈
but they, they knew I didn't want to.
所以这就是难言之隐
And so it just, uh,
something unsaid, you know.
“欢迎回来 文森
"Welcome back, Vince.
你历尽磨难 但欢迎你回来”
You've been through the, the
wringer, but welcome back."
1981年4月
NARRATOR: In April 1981,
8名建筑师和雕塑家组成的评审小组
a panel of eight architects and sculptors
聚集在华盛顿郊外的
gathered in an airplane hangar
安德鲁斯空军基地的一个机库
at Andrews Air Force
Base outside Washington.
在那里他们要从1400多件投稿中
They were there to choose
the winning design
为首都挑选出一个
for a Vietnam memorial
for the nation's capital
越战纪念碑的优胜设计
from more than 1,400 submissions.
纪念碑是一名固执老兵的点子
The memorial was the brainchild
of a single stubborn veteran,
前步兵简.克鲁格斯
a former rifleman named Jan Scruggs,
他在一次可怕的记忆闪回之后
who, after suffering a
frightening flashback,
告诉他的妻子 他想“建一座纪念碑
told his wife he wanted
to "build a memorial
“给所有那些在越南服过役的人
"to all the guys who served in Vietnam.
将会刻上所有阵亡者的名字”
It'll have the name of everyone killed."
和其他老兵一起
With other veterans,
他创立了一个非盈利性组织
he established a nonprofit organization,
越战老兵纪念碑基金会
the Vietnam Veterans Memorial Fund,
致力于募集资金和制订计划
and went to work collecting
money and making plans.
最后约有65万美国人
In the end, some 650,000 Americans
捐出800多万美元
would contribute more than $8 million.
评审们选中了第1026号作品
The judges chose submission number 1026.
（掌声）
(applause)
苏珊.彼特森：21岁的林璎（玛雅.林）
SUSAN PETERSON: 21-year-old Maya Ying Lin,
一名耶鲁大学建筑系学生
an architect student at Yale University,
获得了2万美元奖金
got the $20,000 prize.
她的获奖设计由
Her winning design is comprised
两个细长的三角形黑色花岗岩组成
of two elongated triangles
of black granite,
插入一个斜坡 上面刻着
inset into a hill and
inscribed with the names
越战中57692名死者的名字
of the 57,692 men and women
who died in the war.
林的父母1940年代从中国移民到俄亥俄
Lin, whose parents emigrated
from China in the 1940s to Ohio,
她以为自己不会胜出
thought she wouldn't win
因为她的设计过于独特和强烈
because her design was too
strange and too strong.
我的大致想法是想描述一段旅程
I had a general idea that I
wanted to describe a journey,
一段会让你体验死亡的旅程
a journey that would make
you experience death
在那里你必须是一个观察者
and where you'd have to be an observer,
在那里永远无法完全融入死者
where you could never really
fully be with the dead.
它不会是某种你看了会说
It wasn't going to be something
that was going to say,
“没关系 都结束了”的东西
"It's all right, it's all over,"
因为它不是
because it's not.
对战争的不同看法
NARRATOR: Differences about the war
让人们对获奖设计褒贬不一
colored people's feelings
about the proposed design.
有人认为越战不公正、不道德
Some who believed that the war
had been unjust and immoral
担心纪念碑会有美化之嫌
feared the monument was
somehow meant to glorify it.
另一些人担心它质朴的设计无法表现出
Others feared its stark
design failed to do justice
美国参战原因的正义
to the cause for which
Americans had fought.
作家汤姆.沃尔夫否决它的理由是
The writer Tom Wolfe dismissed it
“对简.方达的致敬”
as "a tribute to Jane Fonda."
汤姆.卡哈特：我不在乎艺术感
TOM CARHART: I don't care
about artistic perceptions.
一个未受过艺术教育的人
One needs no artistic education
看到这个纪念碑设计时觉得它是什么：
to see this memorial design for what it is:
一道黑色伤疤
a black scar.
黑色 世界通行的
Black, the universal color
悲伤、耻辱和堕落的颜色
of sorrow and shame and degradation
世界上所有种族和社会都是如此
in all races and all societies worldwide.
一道裂口里 犹如隐藏着无尽耻辱
In a hole, hidden as if out of shame.
贾尼斯.康纳利：主席先生 委员会成员
JANICE CONNALLY: Mr. Chairman,
members of the commission,
我作为个人发言
I speak as an individual,
普通公众的一员
a member from the general public.
越战中令人难忘的画面是什么？
What are the memorable images
from the war in Vietnam?
一名游击队员
A guerrilla,
被近距离射杀
shot at point-blank range.
一个赤裸女孩 着了火
A naked girl, afire, running,
在尘土路上奔跑尖叫
screaming down a dusty road.
我认为玛雅.林是对的
I think Maya Lin was right
应当超越这样的画面
in going beyond these kinds of images.
她表现出那个悲情时代所有的痛苦与冲突
She resolved all the pain and
conflict of that unhappy time
用一个牺牲的简单信息和静默的英雄主义
in a simple message of
sacrifice and quiet heroism.
在一个支持玛雅.林设计的官方评选中
NARRATOR: In an official vote of
support for Maya Lin's design,
阵亡美军的母亲们道出心声
the American Gold Star
Mothers spoke for many.
她们说“现在”
"Nowadays," they said,
“爱国主义是件复杂的事
"patriotism is a complicated matter.
“但也许这就是为什么
"But perhaps that is why
“V型黑色花岗岩线条
"the V-shaped, black granite lines
“平缓的与斜坡合为一体
"merging gently with the sloping earth
“传达出人们对于战争
"convey the only point about the war
“可能是唯一的共识：
"on which people may agree:
那些死者应该被记住”
that those who died should be remembered."
（西蒙&加芬克尔“恶水之桥”）
("Bridge Over Troubled Water"
by Simon and Garfunkel playing)
♪当你疲惫
♪ When you're weary
♪感觉渺小
♪ Feeling small
♪当你满含泪水
♪ When tears are in your eyes
♪我会全都擦干
♪ I'll dry them all.
雷翁.考西：当你走下车 靠近那道墙
RION CAUSEY: As you got out of the
car and you approached the wall,
它强烈的抓住你..
the intensity of which, it grabs you...
你走上前去..
You go up...
你看到那些名字
You see the names,
你触摸那些名字
you touch the names...
非常强烈
(crying): It's intense.
♪在恶水之桥
♪ Bridge over troubled water
♪我会让自己躺下
♪ I will lay me down.
索利：我不喜欢
SORLEY: I did not like
越战墙
the Vietnam wall.
我认为那是一条丑陋的黑沟
I considered it an ugly, black ditch
它说唯一值得纪念的
and that it said the only people that, uh...
是那些死者
to be commemorated are the dead,
不因为他们是英雄 而是受害者
not because they're heroes,
but because they're victims.
我没去过
I didn't go.
直到..
Until...
某年..
one year...
他们要把花圈放到
they were going to put the
wreath in front of...
我室友的名字前
the name of my roommate.
我不得不去
(voice breaking): I had, I had to go.
所以 从那以后我每年都去
So I've gone every year since then
去记住我们所失去的
to remember those we, we lost.
呃..
And, um...
我走到最左边
I walk down to the far left
我用手指在名字上抚摸
and I run my fingers over that name.
冈本：你去那道墙
You go to that wall,
甚至还有我儿子 我第一次带他去时他9岁
and even my son, who was nine
years old when I first took him,
你看到5万8千个名字
and you see over 58,000 names,
你知道在每个名字后面或旁边没写出的
and you know that unwritten
behind or beside each name,
有一位母亲、父亲、妻子或女儿
there's a mother or a father
or a wife or a daughter
他们的生活被那场该死的战争
whose lives were forever shattered
永远打碎了
by that damn war.
南希.比伯曼：我去过越战墙 不止一次
NANCY BIBERMAN: I've been to
the wall, more than once.
当我回首战争
When I look back at the war and, you know,
想到那些我们对归国老兵
think of the horrible things, you know,
说过的那些可怕的话
we said to, you know,
vets who were returning,
叫他们“婴儿杀手”或更糟的
you know, calling them
"baby killers" and worse,
我..我为此感到很伤心
I, you know... I feel very sad about that.
我只能说 我们也是孩子
I can only say that, you
know, we were kids, too,
和他们一样是孩子
you know, just like they were.
时至今日 这让我伤心
It grieves me, it grieves me today.
让我痛心的想起我说过的话
It pains me to think of
the things that I said
我们说过的话
and that we said.
对不起
And I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
（鸟鸣）
(bird calling)
卡罗尔.克罗克：我不想去
CAROL CROCKER: I didn't want to go.
那是个美丽的夏日早晨
And it was a beautiful summer morning.
先去林肯纪念堂
Went to the Lincoln Memorial first.
一个舒适的地方
A comforting place to be.
接下来..
And...
穿过街道走进入口
And then crossed the street and
walked in towards the entrance.
你知道 起初你压根看不到墙
And, as you know, at first, you
can't really see the wall,
你走下草坡
and you're coming down
into the grassy hill.
当我看到它时
And when I caught sight of it,
我简直无法呼吸
I literally lost my breath.
当然 我哭了
Of course, I wept.
我得设法站高 这样才能摸到它
I had help getting lifted
up so I could touch it.
我找到了我哥哥的名字
I found my brother's name.
我看到我哥哥的名字
I looked at my brother's name
和其他所有的人在一起
in the company of all those other people.
有过悲伤
There was sadness.
但现在他不再孤单
But now he wasn't alone, either.
他和那些人在一起
He was in the company of people.
他在那里
And he was there
让人们了解和思考
for people to know and to think about.
他没有被遗忘
And he wasn't forgotten.
他没有消失
And he wasn't lost.
它不可思议的治愈和解脱了我
It was incredibly healing
and freeing for me.
马斯格雷夫：当我从倒影池走向它时
As I was walking towards it
from the reflecting pool,
墙上有那么多名字
there were so many names on those walls.
突然间我的喉咙肿起
And all of a sudden, my throat swole up,
我想“我做不到
and I thought, "I can't do this.
我现在没法过去”
I can't do this right now."
我崩溃了
And I collapsed.
我一直强忍着泪水..
And all the tears I'd been holding back...
我没有大哭 我在呜咽
I didn't cry, I sobbed.
我双膝跪倒 啜泣着
I was on my knees, sobbing.
我停不下来 无法呼吸
I couldn't stop, I couldn't get my breath.
我感谢上帝 它在那里
And I was so grateful to
God that it was there.
我想
I thought,
“这将会拯救生命
"This is going to save lives.
这将会拯救生命”
This is going to save lives."
瓦列雷：它的美丽让我震撼
VALLELY: I was struck by its beauty
从空中看越南如此安宁
and how at peace Vietnam
looked from the air.
我内心有种期待感
I had a sense of anticipation in my body.
我和另外一些人努力工作数月
I had worked hard for
many months with others
组织了这次旅行
to organize this trip and
to negotiate our arrival
和越南政府交涉访问事宜
with the Vietnamese government.
你好吗？
How do you do?
我叫（越南语）汤姆.瓦列雷
Toi ten Tom Vallely.
瓦列雷：我作为老兵回到越南
VALLELY: I came back to
Vietnam as a veteran
去了解历史
to learn from history,
看看这个地方的变化
and to see how the place had changed.
（笑声）
(laughter)
自1975年以来
There had only been 200 Americans
只有200个美国人到过越南
that had been to Vietnam since 1975,
大部分是在南方
and most of them had been correspondents
待过的通讯记者
and had been in the South.
（叫嚷 鸣笛）
(clamoring, horn honking)
你走在街上 许多孩子
Many of the kids, you'd
walk down the street,
他们会说“Lien Xo”
and they'd go, "Lien Xo, lien Xo,"
意思是“俄国人”
which means "Russian."
而你说“不是俄国人
And you'd go, "Nolien Xo,
我是美国人（越南语）”
toi la nguoi My"... "I'm an American."
他们脸上会放光 他们说“美国人！”
And their face would light up,
and they'd go, "American!"
会象野火一般蔓延
And it would spread like wildfire
到校园或街道
through the schoolyard, or the street
美国人在这里
that Americans were here.
他们会跑出来 非常友好
And they'd come out and they'd
be very, very friendly.
（笑声）
(laughter)
再见
Goodbye.
再见！再见！
Goodbye! Goodbye!
（笑声）
(laughter)
汤姆.瓦列雷曾在越南当过陆战队员
NARRATOR: Tom Vallely had served
with the Marines in Vietnam.
16年后 这个国家吸引他回来
16 years later, the country drew him back.
他在哈佛肯尼迪学院
He founded the Vietnam Program
创立了越南计划
of the Kennedy School at Harvard,
帮助培训这个国家的一些未来领袖
and helped educate some of the
country's future leaders.
我非常非常投入
I got very, very involved
in the reconnecting
美国和越南间的重新联结
between the United States and Vietnam,
重新联结如何做到
and how that reconnection takes place,
我花了10年时间来整合
I spent a decade of my life
putting those pieces together.
虽然美国
NARRATOR: Although the United States
和越南没有外交关系
did not have diplomatic
relations with Vietnam,
老兵们开始自发回来
veterans had begun coming
back on their own,
重访曾经战斗过的地方..
revisiting places where they had fought...
会见老对手..
...meeting old foes...
种树和建学校
...planting trees and building schools,
试图忘掉战争
trying to put the war behind them.
瓦列雷和其他老兵密切合作
Vallely worked closely with other veterans,
包括3位美国参议员
including three United States senators,
他们成为关系正常化
who became among the most
influential American advocates
最有影响力的倡导者：
for normalizing relations:
亚利桑那州的约翰.麦凯恩
John McCain from Arizona,
他当过6年战俘
who had endured six years
as a prisoner of war;
马萨诸塞州的约翰.克里
John Kerry from Massachusetts,
前快艇指挥官
the ex-commander of a Swift Boat;
内布拉斯加州的鲍勃.凯里
and Bob Kerrey of Nebraska,
前海豹突击队员
a former Navy SEAL.
他们的任务并不简单
Their task would not be easy.
河内坚持要美国
Hanoi insisted the United States make good
以承诺提供重建资金示好
on a promise to provide
funds for reconstruction.
美国这边要求获得一份
For its part, the United States demanded
关于2500名
a complete accounting
从未被发现遗体的美国人
of the 2,500 Americans whose remains
完整的记录
had never been recovered.
河内自己的失踪人员超过30万
Hanoi, which had more than
300,000 missing of its own,
他们拒绝合作
refused to cooperate.
但越南国内和境外发生的事件
But events both within Vietnam
and far beyond its borders
缓慢推动着事态发展
slowly moved things along.
保宁：谁意识到这个问题？
是老兵
他们在战场上洒过热血
现在他们回到农村
被迫以那种疯狂的方式生活
在集体农庄里
是农民士兵改变了这个国家
黎笋死于1986年
NARRATOR: Le Duan died in 1986.
他的继任者实行所谓“经济革新”
His successors adopted
what they called doi moi,
一种更务实的改革经济政策
a more pragmatic reformist economic policy.
随着冷战结束 苏联援助消失了
As the Cold War ended,
Soviet aid disappeared,
河内终于开始帮美军
and Hanoi finally began to help U.S.
military teams
寻找美国人遗体
search for American remains.
瓦列雷：正常化的构建者
VALLELY: The architects of normalization
是越南人
are the Vietnamese.
不是美国人
It's not the Americans.
越美关系正常化
And the normalization of Vietnam
是越共的一项策略
is a strategy of the
Vietnamese Communist Party
以加入世界大家庭
to join the world.
他们想加入世界大家庭
They want to join the world.
美国给他们的加入制造困难
And the United States makes it
hard for them to join the world.
所以约翰.麦凯恩坚持
So John McCain insists,
“好 你想正常化？
"Yeah, you want to have normalization?
所有囚犯都要放出再教育营”
All your prisoners need to be
out of re-education camp."
“你想正常化？”
"You want normalization?"
约翰.克里说“我要所有失踪者信息”
John Kerry... "I need all the
information about the missing."
1994年
NARRATOR: In 1994,
在越南人满足美国人要求之后
after the Vietnamese met
the Americans' demands,
美国取消了贸易禁运
the United States lifted its trade embargo.
全面正常化于次年到来
Full normalization came the following year.
美国新任大使是皮特.彼特森
The new American ambassador
was Pete Peterson,
曾作为战俘在河内关押6年
who had spent six years
in Hanoi as a P.O.W.
2000年11月
In November of 2000,
比尔.克林顿总统访问越南
President Bill Clinton traveled to Vietnam,
这是自31年前理查德.尼克松
the first American president
to visit that country
视察美军之后 第一位美国总统
since Richard Nixon reviewed U.S.
troops there
访问这个国家
31 years earlier.
贝拉克.奥巴马：现在我们可以说出
BARACK OBAMA: Now we can say something
曾经难以想象的话：
that was once unimaginable:
今天 越南和美国是伙伴
Today, Vietnam and the
United States are partners.
我们已经表明 人心可以改变
We have shown that hearts can change,
当我们拒绝成为过去的囚徒时
and that a different future is possible
一个不同的未来就有可能
when we refuse to be prisoners of the past.
黎工训：住在城里的一些战友
经常见到美国老兵
他们互相语言不通
但他们很高兴能够见面
他们互相拥抱
他们象老兵对老兵一样互相对待
我们忘掉过去
虽然我身上还留有弹片
我想结束战争这一篇章
现在我们应该向前看
当我们的孩子能去美国上学
从那里学到最精华的东西
了解那里的人民
迈克.希尼：我回到越南
MIKE HEANEY: I went back to Vietnam.
我联系到一个省级老兵组织
I got in touch with a
provincial vets organization.
这是个很大的越南老兵组织
This is a huge organization
of Vietnamese vets,
都是从前的敌人
all former enemies.
All former enemies.
但现在 象我一样 成熟许多
But now, mellowed quite a bit, like me.
和我年纪相仿 都是爷爷辈的
You know, they're guys my age, grandpas.
我们经过初步的互相了解
And after we got past the initial
checking each other out,
只要不涉及政治问题
and is this a political thing or not,
他们便相当亲切和慈爱了
they could not have been more
gracious and more loving.
他们象士兵兄弟那样罩着我
They took me under their
wing like a brother soldier.
我们交换痛苦回忆和故事
We exchanged painful memories, stories.
我举行了一场小型仪式纪念死去战友
And I did a little ceremony
honoring the guys I'd lost,
纪念我们杀死的越南敌人
honoring the Vietnamese
enemies that we'd killed.
告诉他们 他们现在可以安息了
And just telling them, you know,
they could be at peace now.
这是一次非常美好的旅行
It was a wonderful, wonderful trip.
你无法..
You know, you don't...
你无法彻底解脱 但你得到些抚慰
You don't get closure,
but you get some peace.
我得到了一些安慰
You get some peace... I got some peace.
在越南 大地已经基本复原
NARRATOR: In Vietnam, the
land has largely healed.
过去的仇恨大多已被埋葬
Old animosities have mostly been buried.
但还留存着幽灵
But ghosts remain.
美国人和越南人
Americans and Vietnamese
一起去清理那些地方
work together to clean up places
那些被橙剂荼毒了的土地
where Agent Orange has poisoned the earth.
未引爆的炸弹 半埋在地面
Unexploded ordnance,
half-hidden in the ground,
每年依然夺走人们性命
still takes lives each year.
来自北越上了年纪的父母亲
Aged mothers and fathers
from northern Vietnam
仍在南方漂泊
still roam the south,
苦苦探寻
seeking to discover
他们儿女的下落
what happened to their sons and daughters.
鲁克心：我部队里的士兵
他们的父母相信我会照看他们
一些人的尸体从未找到
我整天感到内疚
在梦里战争和死亡的残酷场面纠缠着我
我想这是因为我没有完成我的职责
我没有帮家人找到他们
每天有人打电话问我
“我儿子在这个团那个连当兵
他死在战场上
你找到他了吗？”
我无言以对
阮玉：我想你会说越南战争
是一首英雄赞歌
但也是一个巨大的悲剧
现在 在越南我们开始重新思考这场战争
提出各种问题
战争对于实现正义真是必要的吗？
这是对的吗？
战争结束了
我们要着眼于现在的生活
最重要的是从战争中
为我们的生活找到一些意义和教训
山姆.威尔逊：当我们最终跌跌撞撞离开越南
SAM WILSON: As we finally came
lurching out of Vietnam...
我们开始怀疑自己
We were beginning to doubt ourselves.
对于美国人来说 这是种陌生的感觉
And, uh, that's a foreign
feeling for an American.
我们难得怀疑自己
We, we seldom doubt ourselves.
结果导致了我们整个历史当中
This turned out to be the most
bitter, the most divisive...
最苦涩、最分裂的战争..
or second-most bitter and
second-most divisive...
或许是史上第二的苦涩和分裂
war in our entire history.
我们仍因此受到伤害
And we still hurt because of it.
我们对越南有负罪感
We have feelings of guilt about Vietnam.
战争结束40多年
NARRATOR: More than four
decades after the war ended,
它在美国人之间造成的分裂
the divisions it created between Americans
尚未完全愈合
have not yet wholly healed.
学到教训又被遗忘
Lessons were learned and then forgotten;
分歧弥合又被扩大
divides were bridged and then widened;
旧的秘密被揭露 新的秘密又被锁藏
old secrets were revealed and
new secrets were locked away.
越战是场悲剧
The Vietnam War was a tragedy,
无可估量 无法挽回
immeasurable and irredeemable.
但从那些经历过它的个体故事里
But meaning can be found
in the individual stories
能够找寻出意义
of those who lived through it,
这些故事是关于勇气
stories of courage and comradeship
情谊和坚韧
and perseverance,
关于谅解和宽恕
of understanding and forgiveness
最终是关于和解
and, ultimately, reconciliation.
奥布赖恩：“他们分担往事的沉重
O'BRIEN: "They shared the weight of memory.
【蒂姆.奥布赖恩特】
作家，仍在为他
所经历的追寻意义
“他们挑起别人背不动的东西
"They took up what others
could no longer bear.
“他们经常相互搀扶 伤员或病患
"Often, they carried each
other, the wounded or weak.
“他们携带传染病
"They carried infections.
【卡罗尔.克罗克】
现为纽约上州
一名家庭辅导员
“他们携带象棋 篮球
"They carried chess sets,
“篮球
"basketballs,
【韦德】
成为知名历史学家
现居胡志明市
“越英词典
"Vietnamese-English dictionaries,
“军衔徽章 铜星和紫心勋章
"insignia of rank, Bronze
Stars and Purple Hearts,
【比尔.埃尔哈特】
教师、诗人和作家
住在费城
“行为守则塑料卡
"plastic cards imprinted
with the Code of Conduct.
【杨文梅】
最终与姐姐团聚
写过她家庭悲欢离合的故事
住在加州
“他们承受疾病
"They carried diseases,
【罗杰.哈里斯】
成为一名教育工作者
在波士顿公立学校
工作41年
“其中有疟疾和痢疾
"among them malaria and dysentery.
“他们承受虱子、皮癣、水蛭
"They carried lice and
ringworm and leeches,
【马修.哈里森】
在陆军服役20年后退休
现居康涅狄格州
“稻藻以及各种溃烂和霉菌
"paddy algae and various rots and molds.
【黎明闺】
河内记者和小说家
“他们承受着土地本身..越南
"They carried the land itself... Vietnam,
【哈尔.库什纳】
再婚 眼科医生
现居佛罗里达州
“这个地方 这片土壤..
"the place, the soil...
【卡尔.马兰奇】
住在西雅图附近
花费30年时间写越战小说
“一片橙红的尘土
"a powdery orange-red dust
“掩埋着他们的军靴、工服和脸孔
"that covered their boots
and fatigues and faces.
【梅里尔.麦克皮将军】
第一次海湾战争期间空军主管
现居俄勒冈州
“他们承受着天空
"They carried the sky.
【约翰.马斯格雷夫】
住在堪萨斯州
越战参战人员法律顾问
“整个大气层
"The whole atmosphere,
“他们承受它
"they carried it...
【阮玉】
越南受人尊敬的
教师和作家
“潮湿 季风
"the humidity, the monsoons,
“真菌和腐臭 所有的一切
"the stink of fungus and decay, all of it.
【保宁】
第一位撰写越战的北越士兵
现居河内
“他们承受着重力
"They carried gravity.
“他们象骡子般移动
"They moved like mules.
【文森特.冈本】
洛杉矶县高等法院法官
“白天 他们被冷枪狙击
"By daylight, they took sniper fire;
“夜晚 他们被迫击炮轰击
"at night, they were mortared.
“他们钻坑道 打前哨
"They crawled into tunnels and walked point
【陈玉同】
在再教育营关押9年
现居休斯敦
“弹雨中前行
"and advanced under fire.
“但这不是战斗
"But it was not battle,
【潘全慧】
成为北加州移民法官
“只是永无休止的行军
"it was just the endless march,
“村庄到村庄
"village to village.
【比尔.齐默曼】
南加州政治顾问
“他们为行军而行军
"They marched for the sake of the march.
“他们缓慢笨拙 举步维艰
"They plodded along slowly, dumbly,
“赴汤蹈火 不假思索
"leaning forward against
the heat, unthinking,
“都是血肉之躯 普通一兵
"all blood and bone, simple grunts,
“强拖着双腿
"soldiering with their legs,
“爬上山丘 下到稻田
"toiling up the hills and
down into the paddies
“穿过河流 上下来回 努力前行
"and across the rivers and up
again and down, just humping,
“一步接一步
"one step and then the
next and then another.
“他们让双腿移动
"They made their legs move.
他们在苦熬”（威廉.福克纳名句）
They endured."
【hollyhoon校对整理】
（披头士“随它去吧”）
("Let It Be" by The Beatles playing)
♪ 当我发现自己深陷困境♪
♪ When I find myself
in times of trouble ♪
♪ 玛丽妈妈来到我身旁
♪ Mother Mary comes to me
♪ 给我智慧的指引
♪ Speaking words of wisdom
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 在我最黑暗的时刻
♪ And in my hour of darkness
♪ 她就站在我面前♪
♪ She is standing right
in front of me ♪
♪ 给我智慧的指引
♪ Speaking words of wisdom
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧
♪ Let it be, let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧 ♪
♪ Let it be, let it be ♪
♪ 智慧的指引
♪ Whisper words of wisdom
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 所有伤心的人们♪
♪ And when the brokenhearted people ♪
♪ 生活在这个世界上
♪ Living in the world agree
♪ 都会有一个答案
♪ There will be an answer
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 即使他们被迫分离
♪ For though they may be parted ♪
♪ 他们仍有机会相见
♪ There is still a chance
that they will see ♪
♪ 会有一个答案
♪ There will be an answer
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧
♪ Let it be, let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧♪
♪ Let it be, let it be ♪
♪ 耶 会有一个答案♪
♪ Yeah, there will be an answer ♪
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧
♪ Let it be, let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧♪
♪ Let it be, yeah, let it be ♪
♪ 智慧的指引
♪ Whisper words of wisdom
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 阴云密布的夜空
♪ And when the night is cloudy
♪ 仍有光芒照耀着我
♪ There is still a light
that shines on me ♪
♪ 照耀到明天
♪ Shine until tomorrow
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 我被音乐之声唤醒
♪ I wake up to the sound of music ♪
♪ 玛丽妈妈来到我身边
♪ Mother Mary comes to me
♪ 智慧的指引
♪ Speaking words of wisdom
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 耶 随它去吧 随它去吧
♪ Yeah, let it be, let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧
♪ Let it be, yeah, let it be
♪ 会有一个答案
♪ There will be an answer
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧
♪ Let it be, let it be
♪ 随它去吧 耶 随它去吧
♪ Let it be, yeah, let it be
♪ 会有一个答案
♪ There will be an answer
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be
♪ 随它去吧 随它去吧
♪ Let it be, let it be
♪ 随它去吧 耶 随它去吧
♪ Let it be, yeah, let it be
♪ 智慧的指引
♪ Whisper words of wisdom
♪ 随它去吧
♪ Let it be.
【hollyhoon校对整理】